2PL, how was the concert on Saturday.
2PL ，周六的演唱会怎么样？
It went well, it might be [redline] a bunch of speakers.
很好，会给一群演讲者[]。
What does it mean the redline speaders?
你说的[]演讲者是什么意思？
I mean if the speaker can work at like a 100%,
我的意思是，如果演讲者可以 100% 地工作，
you will working them at 200%.
你会让他们达到 200% 。
Did you break them?
你打破了吗？
Next time maybe.
也许下一次可以。
Okay, nice, how many people showed up?
好的，有多少人？
Two hundred.
两百。
Two hundred, that's impressive.
两百，太令人惊讶了。
Okay and your next show is when?
好的，你的下一场演出是什么时候？
October, after the fall break.
十月份，在秋休之后。
That's off campus though.
那是校外的事。
We'll post that on Piazza.
我们会把它张贴在 Piazza 上。
All right, guys, a lot to cover,
好的，大家，有很多东西要讲，
some quick administrative things, go quickly.
一些快速管理的事情，我很快讲一下。
So the homework #2 is been out,
所以家庭作业 #2 已经放出，
we bumped the due date to be October 4th,
我们把截止日期推迟到了 10 月 4 日，
because we didn't want to have it lined up on the same date that project #1 is due,
因为我们不想让它和项目 #1 的截止日期排在同一天，
so the material part of the problem,
所以问题的材料部分，
I also do is the scheduling with Labor Day everything,
我也做的是劳动节的日程安排，
so the material of that homework discusses things we'll discuss next week,
所以家庭作业的材料讨论，我们下周讨论，
so we postpone that a day
我们把这推迟了一天，
and then project #1 still on track, we due October 2nd
然后项目 #1 仍在正轨上，我们截止 10 月 2 日，
and again that's on a Sunday,
也是在星期天，
we're having the Q&A session this today, Monday at 6:30pm
星期一下午 6：30 ，我们将举行问答会议，
and that'll be on, on Zoom and that's a post on that Piazza
这将是在 Zoom 上，张贴在 Piazza 上，
and then as for all the projects,
至于所有的项目，
again, there won't be any office hours on Sundays,
周日不会有任何办公时间，
when the project is due,
当项目到期时，
but there'll be a special office hours session on the Saturday, before it's due,
但是会有一个特别的办公时间会议，在周六，在它到期之前，
on campus, with like four TAs, between 3 and 5pm,
大约下午 3-5 点之间有 4 个助教，
this is meant to be like a forcing function
这就像是一种强制功能，
for you guys actually start working on the project
让你们真正开始工作，
instead of showing up the dates due to office hours,
而不是在到期日期的办公时间表示，
saying you doesn't compile, right,
说你没有编译，
like we want you, we want you to start sooner rather than later, okay?
我们希望你尽快开始，好吗？
Somebody's already gotten, I think, already gotten a 100% on project #1,
我想有些人已经百分之百地完成了项目一，
even though today's lecture discusses project #1,
虽然今天的讲座讨论的是项目一，
so impressive.
所以，令人印象深刻。
Sorry, how much you expected what?
抱歉，你期望什么是多少？
His question is,
他的问题是，
how much time should we expect to complete the entire project,
我们应该花多长时间来完成整个项目，
I mean, it depends on your background,
我想，这取决于你的背景，
like some people ripped through C++, no problems,
比如有些人用 C++ ，没有问题，
other people struggle, right,
而其他人在挣扎，
project #1 is, is, is,
项目一是，
I mean it's more work than project zero,
我的意思是它比项目零的工作量更大，
it's less [worse] than project #1,
它没有项目一那么糟糕，
it's reasonable,
这是合理的，
it's not bad.
它不是很糟糕。
Any other questions?
还有其他问题吗？
All right, so a bunch of other things, that extracurricular things,
好的，还有一些其他课外活动，
that you can do in the class,
你们可以在课程中做，
today, we're having another Seminar talk
今天，我们将进行另一场研讨会演讲，
from from CMU Dana Van Aken,
来自 CMU 的 Dana Van Aken ，
just talk about OtterTune and the startup that I'm involved in,
谈谈 OtterTune 和我参与的初创公司，
then next week, we'll have one of the co-founders of PostgresML,
下周，我们将有 PostgresML 的联合创始人之一，
this is's a, it's a hosted version of Postgres,
这是 Postgres 的[托管]版本，
where they they put [UDFs]
他们在那里放置 UDF ，
or you can make you can make like PyTorch calls directly in, in SQL,
或者你可以在直接使用 SQL 进行类似于 PyTorch 的调用，
they also been working on a Postgres proxy called PgCat,
他们还做了 Postgres 代理，叫做 PgCat ，
that's written in rust, engaged in popularity,
是用 Rust 写成的，很受欢迎，
and then the week after that,
然后在接下来的一周，
actually not the 18th, October 2nd,
实际上不是 18 日，而是 10 月 2 日，
we'll have the CTO and co-founder of Weaviate
我们将有 Weaviate 的 CTO 和联合创始人，
one of these vector databases,
Weaviate 是一个向量数据库，
come give a talk with us on Zoom.
在 Zoom 上给我们演讲。
Okay.
好的。
Yes.
是的。
His question is,
它的问题是，
is there any internship, any opportunities for any of these companies,
这些公司中有没有实习机会，
absolutely, yes,
当然有，
they figure out a best way for you to contact them,
他们想出一种最好的联系方式，
but, yes, all the companies to hiring.
但是，没错，所有这些公司都是为了招聘。
So there was two big database news in the last week,
上周有两条重大的数据库新闻，
since we last have class,
自从我们上节课以来，
did anybody know they were?
有人知道它们是什么吗？
Postgres release version 16,
Postgres 发布了版本 16 ，
is not a big game changer,
并不是一个很大的游戏规则改变者，
in terms of like they don't have like you know, amazing new features,
他们没有令人惊叹的新功能，
it's a lot of refinement and improvements,
它有很多改进之处，
they're nice to haves, it's, it's, it [],
很高兴他们有，它是，
a game changer improvements be like,
游戏规则的改变者的改进是，
in my opinion, is when they added just in time compilation for WHERE clauses,
在我看来，是他们为 WHERE 子句增加及时编译时，
which we'll cover in a few weeks,
我们将在几周内讨论，
deduplication for B trees is kind of nice,
对 B 树重复数据删除是不错的，
there's a bunch of I/O stuff that's still not in ready for production,
有一堆 I/O 的东西还没有准备好投入生产，
which we'll talk about a little about today,
我们今天会稍微讨论一下，
but like, it's a nice to have,
但是，有是不错的，
Postgres has been putting out releases once a year and it's been kind of nice.
Postgres 每年发布一次，这是一件很好的事情。
And then Databricks announced,
然后， Databricks 宣布，
they raised a series I for 500 million dollars
他们以 5 亿美元的价格融资了第 I 轮，
with a 43 billion Dollar valuation,
估值为 430 亿美元，
that's a lot of money goes goes without saying,
这么多钱是不言而喻的，
yeah, I don't, I don't,
是的，我没有，
Snowflake didn't raise this amount, this amount before they went IPO,
Snowflake 在 IPO 之前没有筹集到这个数额，
but anyway, they're hiring.
但不管怎样，他们都在招人。
All right, so, all right.
好的，所以，好的。
So last class, was we finished up the discussion on the storage aspect of database systems
上一节课，我们结束了关于数据库系统存储方面的讨论，
and was really focusing on how the database system is going to represent data in, in disk,
重点是数据库系统如何在磁盘中表示数据，
we talk about the tuple-oriented storage, log-structure storage, the index-organized storage,
我们讨论了面向 tuple 存储，日志结构存储和索引组织存储，
right now we know what these files look like on disk,
现在我们知道这些文件在磁盘上是什么样子，
how they're broken up into pages,
它们是如何被分解成页面的，
and so today's class and going forward is really about
所以今天的课程和以后的课程是关于，
how do we get those pages from disk,
我们如何从磁盘中获取这些页面，
bring those into memory,
将这些页面放入内存，
and then do something with them.
然后对它们进行一些操作。
And of course, the whole goal of what we're trying to build in this conceptual system we're talking about is
当然，我们试图在这个概念性系统中建立的整个目标是，
having a database system that gives the illusion,
拥有一个数据库系统，它给人一种错觉，
that we have more memory than we actually have,
我们拥有比实际拥有更多的内存，
the database is larger than what fits in memory,
数据库比内存中的大小更大，
we want to make it look like we could fit everything in memory.
我们想让它看起来像可以在内存中容纳一切。
So today is really about,
所以今天真正的主题是，
how do we go get the things we need from disk, those pages,
我们如何从磁盘中获取我们需要的东西，那些页面，
bring them into memory,
将它们带入内存，
and then make decisions on how to remove them
然后决定如何删除它们，
in order to save space when we want to bring new things in.
以便在我们想要引入新东西时节省空间。
All right.
好的。
So there's two key aspects we have to consider
所以，我们必须考虑两个关键方面，
in any decisions we're making on how we move data back and forth in disk.
在做出任何有关如何在磁盘中来回移动数据的决策时。
The first is where do we want to write our pages on disk
第一个是，我们希望将页面写到磁盘上的什么位置，
and how can we lay them out
以及如何布局它们，
in such a way that we can maximize the amount of sequential I/O we are doing,
以一种我们可以最大限度地增加执行顺序 I/O 的数量的方法，
instead of doing random I/O.
而不是执行随机 I/O 。
And the idea here is that,
这里的想法是，
we want to keep pages that are going to used together,
我们希望将要一起使用的页面保留在磁盘上，
possibly close to each other physically on disk,
可能在物理上彼此接近，
so that when something, when a query is running or some task is running inside of our database system,
这样当查询运行或某个任务在我们的数据库系统内运行时，
we have to go fetch a bunch of pages,
我们必须获取大量页面，
we want those pages to be sequential,
我们希望这些页面是连续的，
when we, when we bring those into memory.
当我们把那些页面放入内存时。
Then the next thing to consider is,
然后要考虑的下一件事是，
when we have to go read things in memory,
我们何时必须读取内存中的内容，
and this is typically done on demand, meaning,
这通常是按需完成的，意思是，
we'll see prefetching in a second,
我们将在稍后看到预取，
but you're not just,
但你不仅仅是，
the system just go randomly reading things,
系统只是随机地读取东西，
because it wants to,
因为它想要这样做，
if you insert a bunch of data
如果你插入了一堆数据，
and then you never go read it,
然后你从来没有去读它，
it's not gonna go, go read back into memory
它就不会读回内存，
just for the [] of it, right,
只是为了[]，
and so it's gonna be on demand,
所以，它将按需提供，
we have to go get things from disk and bring them to memory.
我们必须从磁盘中获取东西，并将它们带到内存中。
And then the question's gonna be,
然后问题是，
when do we want to evict that from memory, right,
我们什么时候想要把它从内存中驱逐出去，
what was the last time it's accesssed, how was access,
它最后一次访问是什么时候，如何访问，
was it updated since we brought it into memory
自从我们把它放入内存后它是否更新了，
and therefore we need to write it out,
所以我们需要将它写出去，
we're not going to talk about,
我们不会谈论，
how to make sure that we can,
如何确保我们能够，
save our changes in case of a crash or a failure,
保存我们的更改，以防发生崩溃或故障，
we'll talk a little about that at the end,
我们将在最后讨论这个，
but that will be a foucs, major focus, for major focus of a lecture after the, the midterm,
但这将是期中考试后一节课的主要关注点，
this is really about,
这实际上是关于，
okay, I got to decide what data to evict,
好的，我必须决定要驱逐哪些数据，
how do I make that decision.
我该如何做出这个决定。
And so this is that same diagram I showed before,
这是我之前展示的同一张图，
what we have the database file on disk
我们有数据库文件在磁盘上，
and it's broken up to a bunch of pages,
它被分成了几个页面，
and then now what we're talking about today is,
然后我们今天要讨论的是，
this piece here called the buffer pool,
这个叫做缓冲池的部分，
I'll call it the buffer pool manager,
我称之为缓冲池管理器，
some places or some of systems called the the buffer pool cache, cache manager,
某些地方或某些系统称为缓冲池缓存管理器，
they all basically mean the same thing,
它们基本上都有相同的意思，
it's the memory that the database system is going to allocate from the operating system and control on its own.
它他是数据库系统从操作系统分配内存，并自行控制。
So when you have your execution engine,
所以当你有了你的执行引擎，
it starts doing something,
它开始做一些事情，
like, it's, say it's running a query,
比如，它运行一个查询，
It doesn't have to, but it could,
它不一定非得这样，但它是有可能的，
and at some point, it says I need to get page number two,
在某个点上，它说我需要获取第二页，
so again we go get the page directory from disk,
所以我们从磁盘获取页面目录，
bring that into memory,
并将其放入内存，
if it's not already there,
如果它还不在那里，
look on our page directory
查看我们的页面目录，
and that's going to tell us our page number two,
它将告诉我们第二页，
here's the file and the offset where to find that that particular page,
这是在哪里找到该特定页面的文件和偏移量，
we go fetch that in memory,
我们将其放入内存中，
put into one of our free space in our buffer pool
放入缓冲池中的一个空闲空间，
and then give back the execution engine,
然后返回给执行引擎，
a pointer to that page sitting in the buffer pool.
一个指向位于缓冲池中的页面的指针。
So now let's say,
现在让我们假设，
again, we run some kind of eviction policy, replacement policy
我们运行某种驱逐策略、替换政策，
and we decide to remove page two, for whatever reason,
无论出于什么原因，我们决定删除第二页，
because we need more space,
因为我们需要更多空间，
we run a bunch of other data,
我们运行一堆其他数据，
it doesn't matter,
这都无关紧要，
but now when the execution engine comes back
但是现在，当执行引擎回来，
and says I give me page two again,
并说给我第二页时，
it's not in memory,
它不在内存中，
you got to go to disk and get it,
你必须到磁盘上获取它，
but this time it actually might land in a different location in our buffer pool,
但这一次它可能会落在我们的缓冲池中的不同位置，
and again, our system, the execution engine,
我们的系统，执行引擎，
all the other parts of the system above the buffer pool,
缓冲池之上的系统的所有其他部分，
they should obviously not be, not, not cared that it's now in a different location.
它们显然不应该，不关心它现在在不同的位置。
This is different than mmap, right,
这和 mmap 不一样，
if you mmap a file, the memory map file,
如果你 mmap 一个文件，内存映射文件，
when you bring that in your address space,
当你把它带到你的地址空间，
anytime you jump to that sort of mmap file address space,
任何时候你跳到那个 mmap 文件地址空间，
you're always gonna get the same page
你总是会得到相同的页面，
or the operating system is gonna guarantee that for you,
或者操作系统会为你保证这一点，
it may not be in memory when you access it
当你访问它时，它可能不在内存中，
and you get get installed, get fetches in,
你安装它，获取它，
but it's always gonna be in the same address space.
但它总是在同一个地址空间中。
In our system, we're not going to do that,
在我们的系统中，我们不会这样做，
the same page can be in different locations,
相同的页面可以位于不同的位置，
every time it's brought in and out of memory,
每次它调入和调出内存时，
because we need that freedom,
因为我们需要这种自由，
because who knows what's going to be in memory,
因为谁知道内存中会有什么，
the next time we go fetch a page.
下一次我们去取页面时。
So again, this is much different than calling malloc,
这与调用 malloc 有很大不同，
you call malloc,
你调用 malloc ，
the OS is taking care of this all for you,
操作系统为你处理这一切，
the database system is managing all this memory,
数据库系统管理所有这些内存，
because as we see as we go along,
因为正如我们所看到的那样，
it's always going to be in a better position
它总是处于更好的位置，
to make the best decision how to optimize this.
以做出如何优化这一点的最佳决定。
All right, so for today's agenda,
好的，在今天的议程中，
we're going to talk about high level of what a buffer manager is,
我们将从高级别讨论缓冲区管理器是什么，
talk some optimizations we can add to it,
讨论一些我们可以添加的优化，
the order actually switched,
顺序改变了，
then we'll talk about buffer replacement policies,
然后我们将讨论缓冲区替换策略，
then Disk I/O scheduling,
然后磁盘 I/O 调度，
and then we'll briefly mention that,
然后我们会简单地提到，
there's other memory pools in, in, in our database system,
还有其他内存池在我们的数据库系统中，
that may not be always backed by a buffer pool manager,
可能并不总是得到缓冲池管理器，
might be like an ephemeral cache for certain things.
可能是某些东西的[临时缓存]。
So again, I'm going to call it a buffer pool manager,
所以，我将它称为缓冲池管理器，
the textbook calls a buffer manager,
教科书中称其为缓冲区管理器，
I think Oracle might call the buffer cache,
我想 Oracle 可能会把它称为缓冲区缓存，
we're all talking about the same thing.
我们都在讨论相同的东西。
So at a high level, looks like this,
所以，在高级别上，看起来是这样的，
again, it's just a region of memory that we've allocated from the OS
这只是我们从操作系统分配的一个内存区域，
and we're going to logically chunk it up into fixed size pages,
我们将其逻辑地分成固定大小的页面，
again based on the page size of the database system, right,
根据数据库系统的页面大小，
we said 8, Postgres is 8 kilobytes,
我们说 Postgres 是 8 千字节，
MySQL 16 kilobytes, could have compression sizes, right,
MySQL 是 16 千字节，可以有压缩大小，
doesn't matter,
无关紧要，
we're breaking it up based on those page sizes.
我们根据这些页面大小对其进行了细分。
And then an entry or a location in our buffer pool memory,
然后在我们的缓冲池内存中的一个条目或位置，
that we could use to, to install a page,
我们可以用它来安装页面，
we're going to call that a frame.
我们把它称为 frame 。
So think the system boots up,
所以，考虑系统启动，
it calls malloc, gets a bunch of memory
它调用 malloc ，获取一堆内存，
and then say break it up and divide it up into frames,
然后说将其拆分，并将其划分为 frame ，
and then as the database system or other parts of the the execution engine or whatever start requesting pages,
然后，随着数据库系统或执行引擎的其他部分或任何东西开始请求页面，
we're going to make an exact copy of the pages from disk into memory
我们要将这些页面从磁盘复制到内存中，
and, and put it into one of these frames,
然后放入其中一个 frame 中，
the reason why we have to call it frames is,
我们之所以称之为 frame ，
because we're running out of terms,
因为我们的术语快用完了，
I can't call it a page,
我不能称它为页面，
can't call it a block,
也不能称其为块，
because we've already used that,
因为我们已经使用过了，
can't call it a slot,
不能称之为插槽，
because we have a slot array,
因为我们有 slot array ，
so for whatever reason, we're to call it a frame.
无论出于什么原因，我们称其为 frame 。
All right, so again, so somebody needs page one,
好的，有人需要页面一，
then we go find a free frame in our buffer pool
然后我们在缓冲池中找到一个空闲的 frame ，
and we just copy that page on disk into memory,
然后将磁盘上的页面复制到内存中，
same thing here,
这里也是一样，
I need page three,
我需要页面三，
find a free slot,
找一个空位，
and I copy it into memory here,
然后把它复制到内存中，
but again, here we can see that,
但是，我们在这里可以看到，
page one and page three are not contiguous on disk,
页面一和页面三在磁盘上不是连续的，
because it's page two in between them,
因为页面二在它们之间，
but when we put it in our buffer pool and bring it in a memory,
但当我们将其放入缓冲池并将其放入内存时，
again, we're free to put it in any location that we want,
我们可以自由地将其放在我们想要的任何位置，
it doesn't matter.
这无所谓。
So now when dirty,
所以，现在当出现脏页的时候，
when if if we modify one of these pages,
如果我们修改了这些页面中的一个，
we're not gonna, we're not required to flush the data back to disk right away,
我们不需要立即将数据刷新回磁盘，
and again we will cover durability and and recovery late after the midterm,
我们将在期中考试结束后讨论耐久性和恢复，
but this is a key difference then between like a write through cache or a write back cache, right,
但这是透写缓存和回写缓存之间的关键区别，
the write through cache in the OS,
透写缓存在操作系统中，
when you write something to the cache,
当你将某些内容写入缓存时，
it then gets immediately written out the disk as well,
它也会立即被写出到磁盘，
in a write back cache,
在回写缓存中，
we'll write it in memory,
我们会将其写入内存，
but we're not required to write it back right away,
但我们不需要立即将其写回，
we'll do it at some, some later point,
我们将在以后的某个时候做这件事，
there be a background thread or an eviction policy that do this.
一个后台线程或一个驱逐策略做这件事。
And so we won't talk about this today,
所以我们今天不会讨论这个，
but there'll, there'll be a,
但是这里会有，
think of there a separate log file, write ahead log,
考虑有一个单独的日志文件，预写日志，
that'll keep track of what changes we made,
它将跟踪我们所做的更改，
and we'll make sure that thing gets flushed a disk,
我们将确保将它刷新到磁盘，
before our dirty pages do,
在我们的脏页刷新之前，
we don't have to know that for now,
现在我们不必知道这个，
just to be mindful that even though we may update pages,
只需记住，即使我们可以更新页面，
we're not required to write them back right away in memory.
我们也不需要立即将它们写回，在内存中。
I said that the internal data structure, we're going to use
我说过，我们要使用的内部数据结构，
to keep track of what is actually in our frames
用来跟踪 frame 中实际内容（的内部数据结构），
is going to be called the page table,
将被称为页表，
again, the OS has its own page table,
操作系统也有自己的页表，
this is the database page table,
这是数据库页表，
it's better.
这样更好。
And so it's typically going to be a fixed size hash table,
它通常是一个固定大小的哈希表，
that is just keeping track of,
它只是在跟踪，
here's the, here's all my frames, right,
这是我所有的 frame ，
identified by some frame ID
由某个 frame ID 标识，
and then here's the, here's the page information,
然后这是页面信息，
that's, that's currently residing in that, in that page,
当前驻留在页面中，
I could just be a pointer to where that page is actually located,
我可以只是指向该页面实际位置的指针，
and we I have to protect this page table with with a latch,
我们必须用 latch 来保护这个页表，
which I'll describe in a second,
稍后我会描述一下，
think of a, like a mutex,
把它想象成一个 mutex ，
that allows us to have multiple threads or multiple workers
它允许我们有多个线程或多个 worker
accessing the the the page table, at the same time,
在同一时间访问页表，
I don't want to use term threads
我不想使用术语线程，
and it's, it's better to use terms workers,
最好使用术语 worker ，
because like in Postgres, in older systems,
因为比如在 Postgres 中，在旧的系统中，
they don't, they're not multi threaded, they're multi process
它们不是多线程的，它们是多进程的，
and so, but the idea is still the same,
但是想法仍然是一样的，
we want to make sure that,
我们想要确保，
if there's multiple workers touching things and updating things,
如果有多个 worker 访问和更新东西，
they don't, they don't have,
他们没有，
when we're in the critical sections, we don't break things.
当我们处于临界区时，我们不会破坏东西。
So in addition to keeping track of like,
所以，除了跟踪，
here's the, the pointer to the page in our buffer pool and in the frame,
这里是指向缓冲池和 frame 中的页面的指针，
we're also going to have additional metadata
我们还将拥有附加元数据，
about how the pages are being used throughout the system.
关于页面在整个系统中的使用方式。
So the first thing we would have obviously is a dirty flag,
所以，我们首先有的是一个脏标志，
that tells us whether a query has updated a page
它告诉我们查询是否更新了该页面，
since we last brought it into memory,
自从上次将页面放入内存以来，
we'll also have a Pin or reference counter,
我们还将有一个 Pin 或引用计数器，
that keeps track of the number of, number of workers,
用来跟踪 worker 的数量，
that require this page to remain in memory
它们需要该页面保留在内存中，
and therefore it can't be evicted when we run our eviction policy, right,
因此它不能被驱逐，当我们运行驱逐策略时，
so for each page, page three here,
所以每个页面，这里的页面三，
say there's some query that is accessing it at this given time,
比如在这个给定的时间有一些查询访问它，
so in our page table we have a little counter,
所以，在我们的页表中，我们有一个小的计数器，
says there's at least one worker, that's accessing it,
表示至少有一个 worker 在访问它，
and then now say if a, another query comes along
然后现在，如果一个出现了另一个查询，
and was looking for another page, that's not in our page table,
寻找不在我们的页表中的另一个页面，
we'll put a latch on it, protect it,
我们会放一个 latch 在它上面，保护它，
go fetch the data we need,
去取我们需要的数据，
in this case we need page two,
在这种情况下，我们需要页面二，
we update a free frame in our, in our buffer pool,
我们更新缓冲池中的空闲 frame ，
update the page table to now point to this buffer pool,
更新页表以指向该缓冲池，
update any metadata we need to know about it,
更新任何我们需要了解的元数据，
like, who accessed it,
比如，谁访问了它，
when they last accessed it and so forth,
他们最后一次访问它的时间等等，
and then once this query is done doing whatever its update needs to the page table,
然后，一旦该查询完成了对页表的更新所需的任何操作，
we can release the latch,
我们就可以释放 latch ，
return that worker back to whatever is doing,
将 worker 返回到正在执行的任何操作，
and then now any other worker that comes along looking for page two
然后现在任何其他查找页面二的 worker
will find it in this page table.
都将在此页表中找到它。
Pretty simple, right?
很简单，对吧？
So I used this term latch
所以我用了 latch 这个词，
and purposely did not say lock,
故意不说锁，
anyone guess why.
有人猜猜为什么。
Yes.
是的。
He says the standard locks that we have,
他说，我们拥有的标准锁，
locks and latches we have are different,
锁和 latch 是不同的，
different from who or what.
不同于谁或什么。
So he says,
所以他说，
he said that there's that latches have some database magic,
他说， latch 有一些数据库魔力，
that's better for our purposes versus locks.
这比锁更适合我们的目的。
Not quite.
不完全是。
Yes.
是的。
He said locks for user space,
他说有锁是用户空间的，
I mean, the database system is running in user space,
我的意思是，数据库系统在用户空间运行，
but it's for logical things in the database, correct, yes.
但是为了数据库中的逻辑内容，是的。
So right, so this trips people up,
所以这会让人们绊倒，
when they come from like like a more OS background.
当他们来自更像是操作系统背景的时候。
So in the database world,
所以，在数据库世界中，
we have this distinction between locks and latches,
我们有锁和 latch 之间的区别，
so a locks to protect these higher level concepts or objects in our database,
锁用来保护我们数据库中的这些更高级别的概念或对象，
a tuple, a table, a database,
一个 tuple ，一张表，一个数据库，
I take locks on these things,
我在这些东西上使用锁，
and what will happen is,
接下来会发生的是，
we haven't discussed what transactions are just yet,
我们还没有讨论什么是事务，
but think of like I want to do multiple updates,
但是想象一下，我想要进行多次更新，
it's like multiple round trips of SQL queries,
就像是 SQL 查询的多次往返，
and so if I take a lock on something,
如果我对某个东西加锁，
I want to hold it for the length of that transaction,
我想在事务期间持有它，
and because, he's saying user space,
因为，他说的是用户空间，
but it's like the application is the one that's that's creating these locks
但这就像是应用程序创建了这些锁，
or the database system creating these locks on the behalf of the application,
或者数据库系统代表应用程序创建了这些锁，
we assume that they're stupid
我们假设他们是愚蠢的，
and therefore we need to make sure that they don't have deadlocks or other problems,
因此我们需要确保它们不会出现死锁或其他问题，
so we have to have these additional protection mechanisms
所以我们必须有这些额外的保护机制，
to make sure that the Javascript programmer doesn't do something they shouldn't be doing, right.
以确保 Javascript 程序员不会做他们不应该做的事情。
Latches are the low level internal primitives,
latch 是低级内部原语，
we're going to use to protect the critical sections of our database system, right,
我们使用它来保护数据库系统的关键部分，
and these are what the database system developers are using,
这些是数据库系统开发人员使用的，
you had use in, in project #0, right,
你项目零中使用了，
you have to take a mutex, right,
你必须使用 mutex ，
so a latch is basically like a low level mutex, right.
所以， latch 就像一个低级别的 mutex 。
And because, this is meant to be,
因为，这意味着，
latches are being used by the database system developers, meaning us, right,
latch 被数据库系统开发人员使用，也就是我们，
it's not going to have the, the, the deadlock detection and other protection mechanisms we need,
它不会有我们需要的死锁检测和其他保护机制，
because if we're the ones building a database system,
因为如果我们是构建数据库系统的人，
we need to be smart enough to make sure we don't have deadlocks.
我们需要足够聪明，以确保我们不会有死锁。
And so latches are really meant to be like quick in and out critical section,
所以， latch 意味着快速进出临界区，
do something and release it,
做一些事情，然后释放它，
and we need to through through programmer discipline, we need,
我们需要通过程序员[纪律]，我们必须，
we're the ones, we have to make sure that, we don't, don't have deadlocks,
我们必须确保我们不会有死锁，
now, this is confusing,
现在，这是令人困惑的，
because this is also in C++ the standard library,
因为在 C++ 标准库中，
there's also, they use the term latches,
他们也使用术语 latch ，
but that's just a countdown barrier,
但只是一个 countdown barrier ，
we don't want that, we don't need that,
我们不想这样，我们不需要那个，
we're going to roll around latches,
我们要轮询 latch ，
we'll see this more next week,
下周，我们会更多地看到这个，
when we talk about index concurrency control for B+ trees,
当我们讨论 B+ 树的索引并发控制时，
but for now, just assume you can treat it as a mutex,
但就目前而言，你可以将其视为 mutex ，
we don't want to use the OS metux,
我们不想使用操作系统的 mutex ，
that has other problems,
它有其他问题，
we'll cover that later.
我们稍后会讲到。
All right, again, another importantent distinction,
好的，另一个重要的区别，
I've already said this,
我已经说过，
between the page directory and the page table.
在页面目录和页表之间（的区别）。
The page directory is just the the a disk residenton mapping
页面目录只是磁盘的驻留映射，
between page IDs and their locations on the physical disk on, on the actual files themselves,
在页面 id 与它们在物理磁盘上、实际文件上的位置之间，
but the page table is gonna be this ephemeral in memory memory mapping,
但页表将是内存中的短暂映射，
that we use to identify for a given page id,
我们使用它来标识给定的页面 id ，
here's the frame where it's actually located
这是 frame 实际所在的位置，
and if it's not in our page table,
如果它不在我们的页表中，
we know we have to look in the page directory
我们知道我们必须在页面目录中查找，
to go find where it is on disk
以找到它在磁盘上的位置，
and go bring it in, right.
并将其带入进来。
So most of the time the query is going to be hitting up the page table,
所以，在大多数情况下，查询将命中页表，
but it's only when the page table says something's not there,
但只有在页表表示不存在的情况下，
then there needs to be some mechanism through,
然后需要有一些机制，
like the disk scheduler or something,
比如磁盘调度器或其他东西，
that says, all right, let me look at the page directory,
比如，好的，让我看看页面目录，
let me go get the fetch the page from disk
让我去取磁盘上的页面，
and then put it into the page table.
然后把它放到页表中。
Okay?
好的？
So what I've shown you so far is a basic page table,
到目前为止，我向你展示的是一个基本的页表，
it's a hash table, some extra metadata,
这是一个哈希表，一些额外的元数据，
if the page is there,
如果页面在那里，
for given page id,
对于给定的页面 id ，
you get back a pointer to it,
你得到指向它的指针，
if it's not there,
如果它不在那里，
there's some mechanism to go get get it from disk,
有某种机制可以从磁盘获取它，
then install it into a free frame,
然后将其安装到一个空闲的 frame 中，
then the page table has has the entry, right.
然后页表具有该条目。
But this is going to be, this is going to be a big bottleneck
但这将是一个巨大的瓶颈，
unless we're clever and smart about exploiting the information we know
除非我们聪明地利用我们所知道的信息，
about what is going on inside our database system,
关于数据库系统中发生的事情，
for us, to make decisions,
对于我们来说，我们要决定，
how we want to allocate things
如何分配东西，
and and decide who gets what page, at what time and what location
决定谁得到什么页面，什么时间，什么位置，
and what how we decide to evict things,
以及我们决定如何驱逐东西，
because if we don't do, we don't want to exploit the information,
因为如果我们不利用这些信息，
we know about what our queries want to do,
我们知道我们的查询想要做什么，
what our data looks like,
我们的数据是什么样子，
what our access patterns are,
我们的访问模式是什么，
then we're no better than the OS,
那么我们并不比操作系统更好。
the OS doesn't see anything going on inside our database system,
操作系统没有看到我们的数据系统内部发生任何事情，
so, you know, if we just blindly go take requests and go take them out,
所以，如果我们只是盲目地接受请求，然后把它们拿出来，
we're no better than the OS, right.
我们并不比操作系统好多少。
So some of these techniques we'll talk about, these optimizations,
所以，我们将讨论一些技术，一些优化，
this is going to motivate why we need to write our own buffer pool manager,
这将激励我们为什么需要编写自己的缓冲池管理器，
why we don't want to use OS,
为什么我们不想要使用操作系统，
and it would be a combination of policies,
它将是一些策略的组合，
that will affect all queries of running at the same time,
影响所有同时运行的查询（的策略），
or it could be things that are gonna just help a, a single query by itself,
或者，它可能只会帮助单个查询本身，
maybe not necessarily worrying about other queries that are running the same time,
可能不一定担心同时运行的其他查询，
but we can isolate the decisions we make for that query,
但我们可以隔离对该查询所做的决策，
so that they don't try not to affect others, right.
以便它们不会影响其他查询。
And I'm not going to say one of these approaches can be better than another,
我不会说这些方法中的一种会比另一种更好，
but you will see that as we go along,
但你会在我们进行的过程中看到，
all the major database systems are going to use some combination of all of them,
所有主流的数据库系统都将使用它们的某种组合，
or some of them, most of them, right,
或者它们中的一些，或者大多数，
so I can't say you know which one is the most important one to implement first,
我不能说哪一个是首先要实现的最重要的一个，
but we'll see as we go along.
但是随着我们进行，我们将会看到。
All right, so the things I talk about is,
好的。所以我要说的是，
using multiple buffer pools,
使用多缓冲池，
actually, that's probably the first one I take back,
这可能是我说的第一个，
what I said,
正如我所说的，
multiple buffer pools is obvious thing to do first,
首先，多缓冲池是明显要做的，
we'll see what that looks like,
我们看看它是什么样子的，
pre-fetching is more complicated, scan sharing and then buffer pool bypass.
预取是更复杂的，扫描共享，然后是缓冲池旁路。
All right, so, my toy example I shared the beginning,
好的，我在开头分享的玩具例子，
we said there was one page table, one set of frames,
我们说只有一个页表，一组 frame ，
and that was it for the entire system, right.
整个系统就是这样。
But then again, because there's multiple workers running at the same time,
但又说回来，因为有多个 worker 同时运行，
we had to use these latches to protect the data structure,
我们必须使用这些 latch 来保护数据结构，
and for a large number of CPU cores or large number of workers running at the same time,
对于大量 CPU 核心或同时运行的大量 worker ，
those latches are going to become a bottleneck, right.
这些 latch 将成为瓶颈。
We can, because it's fixed,
我们可以，因为它是固定的，
assuming the page table is fixed size,
假设页表是固定大小，
we don't have to have a latch for the entire page table,
我们不必为整个页表设置 latch ，
have latch for individual pages or, or locations in, in the hash table,
为单个页面或哈希表中的位置设置 latch ，
but even then,
但即使这样，
if everybody's trying to go get the same small number of pages,
如果每个人都想获取相同的少量页面，
then those latches are gonna be a, a bottleneck, right.
那么这些 latch 将成为一个瓶颈。
So an easy way to alleviate this contention point is
所以缓解这种争用点的一个简单方法是，
to have multiple buffer pools,
拥有多个缓冲池，
so I still allocate the same amount of memory,
所以我仍然分配相同数量的内存，
so I have to tell the database system when I boot up,
所以我必须在启动时告知数据库系统，
I want 10 gigs of memory, for my buffer pool,
我想要 10GB 的内存，对我的缓冲池，
but I'm going to take those 10 gigs
但是我要用这 10GB ，
and I can divide it into equal size chunks,
我可以把它分成大小相等的块，
and then now have a separate page table for each of them.
然后，现在它们每个都有一个单独的页表。
It also ensures that,
它还确保，
that for certain access patterns on certain data structure,
对于特定数据结构上的特定访问模式，
sorry, certain objects in the database,
抱歉，数据库中的特定对象，
I can have different policies,
我可以有不同的策略，
that can affect one buffer pool versus another,
可以影响一个缓冲池或另一个，
based on how I know that object is going to be used.
根据我知道对象将被使用的方式。
So for example, in, in DB2,
例如，在 DB2 中，
DB2 probably has the the most sophisticated buffer pool management configurations,
DB2 可能具有最复杂的缓冲池管理配置，
where you can actually define a table space,
你可以定义一个表空间，
like a namespace,
与名称空间类似，
and that is backed by a given buffer pool,
并且由给定的缓冲池支持，
you can set what the page size should be for that buffer pool
你可以设置该缓冲池的页面大小，
and you can tell which tables will be managed or indexes will be managed by that buffer pool.
并且你可以知道该缓冲池将管理哪些表或哪些索引。
So let's say you have like one table that is is primarily used for random access,
假设你有一个主要用于随机访问的表，
you could have some policies,
你可以有一些策略，
eviction policies based on, you know, for that, that's optimal for random access,
驱逐政策基于最好的随机访问，
then you have another, another buffer pool,
然后，你有另一个缓冲池，
that's for these other tables, you're doing sequential scans,
用于其他进行顺序扫描的表，
so you have different buffer policies for that sequential scan,
所以，你对该顺序扫描有不同的缓冲区策略，
maybe use larger page page sizes, right.
也许可以使用更大的页面大小。
As far as I know, DB2 is the only one that lets you do this,
据我所知， DB2 是唯一一个允许你这样做的，
I haven't seen Postgres, MySQL certainly can't do this,
我还没有看到 Postgres ， MySQL 肯定不能做这个，
and I don't know about the other enterprise ones,
我不知道其他企业的情况，
but like the DB2 one is very sophisticated.
但像 DB2 是非常复杂的。
And again, this allows you to customize the buffer pool management
同样，这允许你定义缓冲池管理，
for exactly how that object is going to be used.
针对对象的确切使用方式。
Now the question is,
现在的问题是，
how do you find at runtime what buffer pool manager should you use.
如何在运行时发现应该使用哪个缓冲池管理器。
So let's say a really simple example,
让我们举一个非常简单的例子，
here I have two buffer pools
这里我有两个缓冲池，
and so the first thing I can just do is, is,
所以我可以做的第一件事是，
as I said in the DB2 case,
就像我说的，在 DB2 案例中，
I can assign a buffer pool [do to] back a given object
我可以分配一个缓冲池来支持给定的对象，
based on some kind of identifier,
根据某种标识符，
like table one, two, three, table, whatever, that's buffer pool #1
比如表 1 2 3 等等，这是缓冲区一，
and all, all other tables are buffer pool #2.
所有其他的表是缓冲区二。
So, now runtime, when I have a request,
所以，在运行时，当我有一个请求时，
this is obviously not SQL,
这显然不是 SQL ，
but somehow I got through index look up,
但我通过索引查找，
I figured out that I want to look at record one, two, three,
我想我要查找记录一二三，
and we saw before how we can break the record ID into its individual components,
我们在前面看到了如何将记录 ID 分解为其单独的组成部分，
usually like a page ID or a slot number,
通常如页面 ID 或插槽编号，
but in case a SQL Server,
但是对于 SQL Server ，
it also had a file number or object ID,
它也有文件号或对象 ID ，
so we can use this from the record ID,
我们可以对记录 ID 使用这个，
then you'll look up and say,
然后你会查看说，
okay, you know, object four, five, six, that's managed by buffer #1,
好的，对象 4 5 6 ，它由缓冲区一管理，
and then send the request to that buffer pool,
然后将请求发送到那个缓冲池，
and all the requests for other other objects may end to another buffer pool,
而对其他对象的所有请求可能会结束到另一个缓冲池，
and I've isolated them,
我已经将它们隔离，
so that there's less last contention between the two of them.
以便它们之间的最后争用较少。
The simplest approach,
最简单的方法，
then, is to do, what MySQL does is,
MySQL 所做的那样，
you just take the the record ID,
你只需获取记录 ID ，
hash it, modify the number of buffer pool managers you have
对其进行散列，修改你拥有的缓冲池管理器编号，
and that tells you which one you go to, right,
这会告诉你要转到哪个（管理器），
pretty simple.
很简单。
Yes.
是的。
Yeah, so, so he said that the question is,
是的，所以他说的问题是，
do you have to statically allocate how much memory each buffer pool has,
你是否必须静态地分配每个缓冲池有多少内存，
yes, and so in in Postgres, MySQL, in most systems,
是的，在 Postgres MySQL 中，在大多数系统中，
you cannot change the size of the buffer pool
你无法更改缓冲池的大小，
without actually having to restart the entire system,
如果不重新启动整个系统，
actually, in that all the open source systems have that limitation,
事实上，所有的开源系统都有这个限制，
the commercial systems could be kind of clever
商业系统可以是一种聪明的，
and like I think in Oracle,
比如，我认为在 Oracle 中，
you can, you can increase the buffer pool size
你可以增加缓冲池大小，
and it'll allocate the memory
它将分配内存，
and then slowly increment and migrate pages over from page to the next, right,
然后缓慢增加并将页面从一页迁移到下一页，
that's a tricky thing,
这是一件棘手的事情，
but most systems are statically allocated.
但大多数系统都是静态分配的。
Yeah, so his question is could this,
是的，所以他的问题是，
could this mean that you potentially wasting memory,
这是否意味着你潜在地浪费内存，
if you partition say by table,
如果你按表分区，
so for example, if I, if I say,
例如，如果我，
I make a new buffer pool,
如果我创建了一个新的缓冲池，
I put, I say it has 10 gigs
假设它有 10GB ，
and I say you're gonna manage this table,
我说你要管理这个表，
but I don't put any data in that table,
但我没有在那个表中放任何数据，
is that wasting space,
这是在浪费空间吗，
yes,
是的，
but like the database system did exactly what you wanted to do,
但是数据库系统做的是你想做的，
the human was stupid, right,
人类是愚蠢的，
I mean, there's not,
我是说，这里没有，
yeah, because the problem, it doesn't know,
是的，因为问题，它不知道，
you think, okay, well, only allocate it when demand is needed,
你在想，好的，只在需要需求的时候分配它，
but like, the amount of engineering effort to, to sort of accommodate stupid people,
但是就像，为了容纳愚蠢的人而做出的工程努力的数量，
it's probably not worth it in that case, right.
那样的话可能就不值得了。
If you're using DB2,
如果你使用的是 DB2 ，
in theory, you know,
理论上，你知道，
if you're calling create buffer pool the command to do it,
如果你调用 create buffer pool 命令来执行它，
you kind of should be knowing what you're doing, right, like.
你应该知道自己在做什么。
All right, so again, in my opinion,
好的，在我看来，
I think about what I said,
我想我所说的，
this is actually the first optimization you do
这是你做的第一个优化，
to scale your buffer pool manager,
以扩大你的缓冲池管理器，
because it's not that much, much work,
因为这不是那么多的工作，
the hashing one probably the easiest one to do as well,
哈希可能也是最容易做的，
because there's no central data structure to say,
因为没有中央数据结构可以说，
okay, for this object, go to this one,
好的，对于这个对象，转到这个，
you just hash it and you're done.
你只需对它进行哈希，就完成了。
The next optimization we can do is pre-fetching,
我们可以做的下一个优化是预取，
again, the OS to do pre-fetching,
操作系统也做预取，
we'll see for simple cases,
我们将看到，在简单的情况下，
where you're doing sequential scans,
当你在执行顺序扫描时，
we'll see one case, where it can't do it.
我们将看到一个无法执行预取的情况。
So the basic idea is that,
所以基本的想法是，
if you run a query
如果你运行一个查询，
and it has to start accessing data in your table,
它必须开始访问表中的数据，
it's going to open up a cursor,
它将打开一个 cursor ，
that start scanning through the page one by one,
开始逐个扫描页面，
and so assuming this in our example here,
所以，假设在我们的示例中，
our buffer pool is empty,
我们的缓冲池是空的，
so the very first page that it sees page0,
所以，它看到的第一个页面是 page0 ，
it's not in the buffer pool,
它不在缓冲池中，
so we again, we just go copy and put that in,
所以，我们只是去复制并把它放进去，
then we scan along,
然后随着我们扫描，
we need page1, page1 is not there,
我们需要 page1 ， page1 不在那里，
so go go goes ahead and copy that,
所以继续并复制它，
but now the database system can be smart and say,
但现在数据库系统可以聪明地说，
okay, well, you've read page0, read page1,
好的，你已经读取 page0 page1 ，
it's very likely you're gonna read page 2, 3 and, and so and so forth,
很可能你会读 page2, page3 等等，
so let me go ahead and pre-fetch those guys,
所以让我预取这些（页面），
while the database system is processing page1,
当数据库系统处理 page1 时，
all right, go get page2, page3, put it in,
好的，去拿 page2 page3 ，把它放进去，
so that by the time you're finished processing page1
这样当你处理完 page1 时，
and you come to page2,
你来到 page2 ，
[] and behold, the page you're looking,
你正在寻找的页面，
the next page you need is already there, right,
你需要的下一页已经在那里了，
and just do this all the way down the line, right.
从头到尾一直这样做。
We haven't talked about how we execute queries just yet,
我们还没有讨论如何执行查询，
but typically the way it works is that,
但通常它的工作方式是，
you request a page,
你请求一个页面，
it's going to have a bunch of tuples in it,
它在其中有一堆 tuple ，
you do some kind of computation inside the data, that's in those tuples,
你在这 tuple 中的数据上进行某种计算，
and then when you're done,
然后当你完成后，
go get the next page,
转到下一页，
as you're doing your scan along the leaf nodes of the query plan tree.
当你沿着查找计划树的叶子节点进行扫描时。
And so it's not like we're just blindly ripping through the pages
所以，我们并不是盲目地翻阅页面，
and say, you know, get, get, get, get,
然后说，获取，获取，获取，获取，
it get some think time, do some compute,
它得到一些思考时间，做一些计算，
then go get the next page,
然后去拿下一页，
and so that think time is where the database system say,
所以思考时间就是数据库系统说的，
I I have some time to go ahead
我有一些时间继续，
and pre-fetch the things that that you're needing, right.
去预取你需要的东西。
And I don't have the diagram here,
我这里没有图表，
but this is why we have that, that [pinning] mechanism before, right,
但这就是为什么我们以前有那个[钉住]机制，
I don't obviously don't want to fetch in page1,
我显然不想取 page1 ，
then the database system says, in a background thread,
然后数据库系统说，在后台线程中，
okay, let me go prefetch page3 and 2
好的，让我去预取 page3 和 page2 ，
and it goes and swaps out page1,
它会交换 page1 ，
while you're still accessing it, right,
当你仍然访问它时，
the pin will will, the [pinning] mechanism will prevent that.
[钉住]机制将防止这种情况发生。
Yes.
是的。
This question,
这个问题，
good point, thank you,
说得好，谢谢，
his question is,
他的问题是，
is it possible for different buffer, buffer pools to hold the same page,
不同的缓冲池是否可能保存相同的页面，
no.
不会。
It's, it's always been a one more [correspondent],
它总是多一个[匹配]，
every page can only exist in one buffer pool,
每个页面只能存在于一个缓冲池中，
because think about what would happen if you allowed that, right,
因为考虑一下如果你允许这个会发生什么，
well, you could have the page table pointed the same, point to the same page,
好的，你可以把页表指向相同的页面，
different page point to the same page,
不同的页面指向相同的页面，
but then depending where the metadata is,
但取决于元数据的位置，
like the reference counter, the pin marker and things like that,
如引用计数器、[插针]标记和类似的东西，
like if that's separate and separate pages,
如果这是单独的页面，
then then one buffer pool may say,
那么一个缓冲池可能会说，
okay, no one's access to it,
好的，没有人访问它了，
let me, let me go swap it out,
让我把它交换出去，
but the other page table has it, has it pinned
但另一个页表被固定了，
and you would miss that.
你可能会错过它。
So yeah, for that reason,
所以，出于这个原因，
it's a one one correspondent.
这是一对一的匹配。
That's a good point, thank you.
这是很好的观点，谢谢。
Yes.
是的。
This question is,
这个问题是，
what's the relation between a pin counter and a latch,
pin counter 和 latch 之间的关系是什么，
a pin counter just says that,
一个 pin counter 只表示，
there's some, some,
这里有一些，
so, the pin counter says,
所以， pin counter 表示，
there's some worker that's accessing this page,
有一些 worker 正在访问这个页面，
but I'm not in the page table,
但我现在不在页表中，
right now, when I'm doing it, right,
我正在做的，
I get the pointer to the page,
我会将指针指向页面，
go back to my original diagram.
返回到我的原始图表。
Right, going back here,
好的，回到这里，
so I don't on the page table,
所以我不在页表上，
but like this guy says,
但就像这个说的，
give me page #2,
给我页面二，
I take a latch in the page table
我在页表中使用 latch ，
to go get the pointer to that, to that page,
去获取指向那个页面的指针，
and then before I get the pointer back to my execution engine,
然后在我把指针放回我的执行引擎之前，
I pin it,
我把它[钉住]，
because now I'm not inside the page table,
因为现在我不在页表中，
because the pin is latch of protecting the data structure,
因为 latch 保护数据结构，
but I'm out of the data structure,
但我不在数据结构中，
but I have a reference to the page,
但我有一个对页面的引用，
so the pin is supposed to say,
所以， pin 应该表明，
someone is actually reading this page
有人读取这个页面，
and then when I'm done, done with it,
然后当我完成它时，
I can then, you know, decrement the reference counter,
我可以递减引用计数器，
which potentially unlock the or release the pin,
这可能会解锁或释放 pin ，
and then now the buffer pool manager can decide,
然后现在缓冲池管理器可以决定，
okay, I know for this page #2,
好的，我知道对于这个页面二，
nobody has it pinned,
没有人将其钉住，
there's nobody referencing it,
没有人引用它，
so it's, I'm free to evict it.
所以我可以自由地驱逐它。
So again, the latch protects the data structure,
所以， latch 保护数据结构，
the pin pin protects the page.
pin 保护页面。
Yes.
是的。
All right, question is that, the, the.
好的，问题是。
Page tables like separate from the buffer pool?
页表是从缓冲池中分离出来的？
It is the buffer pool.
它就是缓冲池。
I guess like.
我想是。
Yeah, this is like a diagram,
是的，这是一张图表，
but like, it's in this box, how about that.
但它在这个盒子中，这个怎么样。
Right, these are, these are the frames,
这些是 frame ，
there are some other page table data structure here.
这里还有一些其他的页表数据结构。
So his question is,
所以，他的问题是，
does the buffer pool manager have access to the query plan,
缓冲池管理器是否需要访问查询计划，
no, right, because we have these layers,
不，因为我们有这些层，
but you can send it hints,
但你可以给它发提示，
BusTub doesn't support those hints,
BusTub 不支持这些提示，
like I'm, I'm accessing this page,
比如，我正在访问这个页面，
and here's likely the next pages I'm going to access as well,
这是我接下来要访问的页面，
yes, then you said something about static?
是的，然后你说了一些关于静态的事情？
What do you might [statically] know?
从[静态]角度看，可能知道什么？
Okay, so his question is,
好的，所以他的问题是，
if I have a SELECT query,
如果我有一个 SELECT 查询，
who's figuring out what the prefetch,
正在计算预取，
maybe that's what you're really asking,
也许这是你真正想问的，
this has to [] the execution engine,
这必须对执行引擎，
the buffer pool manager doesn't know about,
缓冲池管理器不知道，
it's just, yeah, it's, it's sort of division responsibilities,
它只是，是的，这是一种[部门]职责，
like the [] manager shouldn't have to infer,
比如[]管理器不应该推断，
like for this query plan on on this table, what page that I'm gonna read,
比如对于这个表上的查询计划，我将要读取的页面，
that all comes down below,
这一切都归结到下面，
because you think about it too, that's where,
因为你也想过，那是，
the execution has to know what page it needs to read anyway,
执行必须直到需要读取哪一页，
because as to read them,
因为这样才能读取它们，
so all that logic is in that part of the system,
所以所有的逻辑都在系统的这一部分，
which we'll cover in two weeks.
我们将在两周内讨论。
Yeah, execution engine should say,
是的，执行引擎应该会说，
I'm fetching page1 now,
我现在正在取回 page1 ，
but by the way, I'm also gonna fetch page 2 and 3, right,
但顺便说一句，我也会取回 page2 和 page3 ，
because think about it,
因为想象一下，
like you could have a,
你可以有一个，
you could have like, in your SELECT clause, in the query here,
比如在你的 SELECT 语句中，在这个查询里，
you could have a LIMIT 10, right,
你可以有一个 LIMIT 10 ，
with no where clause,
没有 WHERE 语句，
so in the first page I got five tuples,
在第一页中，我得到五个 tuple ，
in the second page,
在第二页中，
or page0, I got five twoils,
或者在 page0 中，我获得五个 tuple ，
in page1, I got two tuples,
在 page1 ，我得到五个 tuple ，
therefore, I know I'm gonna have to read more pages,
因此，我知道我必须读取更多页面，
so you can send that hint, you know, ahead of time or something like that.
这样你能提前发送提示或类似的东西。
Again, that's the beauty of having a declarative language like SQL,
再次，这就是拥有像 SQL 这样的声明性语言的好处，
where you know what you're going to do ahead of time, right,
你可以提前知道要做什么，
at least at a high level,
至少在高级别上，
with enough, you have enough information where you could make these kind of decisions.
你有足够的信息来做出这样的决定。
So the question is,
所以问题是，
do you never pre-fetch pages
你是否永远不预取页面，
unless you're absolutely certain you're going to need them,
除非你绝对确定你会需要它们，
maybe that's what you're asking?
也许这就是你要问的？
Actually, I don't. I don't know how aggressive they are, yeah,
事实上，我不知道他们有多激进，是的，
the commercial systems do this much better
商业系统在这方面做得要好得多，
and they obviously closed source,
他们显然是闭源的，
so schedule scans is pretty easy for index scans,
所以，对于索引扫描来说，计划扫描非常容易，
next slide,
下一张幻灯片，
this one can be kind of tricky as well,
这个问题也可能有点棘手，
because, you may not be able to prefetch,
因为，你可能无法预取，
without following along the the pages as much,
如果不跟着页面走，
you may, may not be to jump ahead,
你可能就不会跳到前面去，
so I think in index scans, the prefetching is a bit more conservative,
我认为在索引扫描中，预取稍微保守一些，
sequential scan, you could just, you know, you can jump a lot farther.
顺序扫描，你可以跳得更远。
We haven't been talking about,
我们还没有讨论，
like there's all a bunch of other factors, too,
还有一大堆其他因素，
as always the case in databases,
总是在数据库中，
like there's, there's like multi versioning,
比如，有多版本控制，
so who knows whether like,
所以谁知道是不是，
you know, yes, the next page I'm gonna read has 10 tuples,
我要读的下一个页面有 10 个 tuple ，
but like only three may be visible,
但可能只有三个是可见的，
it's complicated.
这很复杂。
All right, so, going back here,
好的，回到这里，
sequential scans, the OS can kind of do this,
顺序扫描，操作系统可以在某种程度上做到这个，
assuming your pages are contiguous,
假设你的页面是连续的，
the OS read ahead can can kind of figure this out,
操作系统预读可以在某种程度上解决这一问题，
what it can't do is
它不能做的是，
infer the the logical data structure that the pages represent physically represent
推断页面物理表示的逻辑数据结构，
and prefetch according to that,
并根据它进行预取，
because again, it doesn't know what B+ tree is,
因为它不知道 B+ 树是什么，
doesn't know what a hash table is,
不知道哈希表是什么，
at least in the at the page level,
至少在页面级别，
but we do, because we're the database system,
但我们能，因为我们是数据库系统，
we, we're the ones actually running it.
我们真正运行它。
Let's say, I have a query,
假设我有一个查询，
like the SELECT * FROM A WHERE val BETWEEN 100 AND 250,
比如 SELECT * FORM A WHERE val BETWEEN 100 AND 250 ，
and I can do this, by reading, by doing an index scan,
我可以通过做索引扫描来实现这个，
we haven't talked about B+ trees yet,
我们还没有讨论过 B+ 树，
but again it's a tree data structure,
但是，它是一种树数据结构，
that shouldn't be foreign to anyone in this class,
对于这门课上的任何人来说都不应该是陌生的，
and then assume that along the leaf nodes,
然后假设沿着叶节点，
the the values are sorted based on on the key, right.
基于键对值进行排序。
So, to to do this run this particular query,
所以，为了运行这个特定的查询，
I had to sort of the root node,
我必须对根节点进行排序，
that's page0, I go get that,
这是 page0 ，我去拿它，
put that in my database, put that in my buffer pool,
把它放到我的数据库里，放到我的缓冲池里，
then I traverse down to this side of the tree,
然后我向下走到树的这一边，
I get page1, put that in my buffer pool,
我得到 page1 ，把它放到我的缓冲池里，
but then now I'm gonna jump down to this leaf node here
但现在我要跳到这里的这个叶节点，
and because I have this this WHERE clause,
因为我有这个 WHERE 子句，
that is gonna be reading, you know, so so many, so many records,
要读取这么多记录，
I know I need to at least go to over to to page5, right,
我知道我至少要到 page5 ，
so I'll go get page, sorry, I will get page3,
所以，我得到，抱歉，我得到 page3 ，
but also can potentially prefetch page5,
但也可以潜在地预取 page5 ，
but again, the operating system can't do this, can't know this,
但是同样，操作系统不能做到这个，不能知道这个，
because, page3 and page5 are not contiguous,
因为， page3 和 page5 不是连续的，
the database system knows,
数据库系统知道，
because it knows that if I least get the index-page3,
因为它知道如果我至少获得了 index-page3 ，
I have a sibling pointer, a page ID,
我就有一个兄弟指针，一个页面 ID ，
so I know what the next next page I'm going to read
所以我知道我要读取的下一个页面，
over along the leaf nodes as I scan across,
在我扫描时，沿着叶节点，
so therefore I can go ahead and prefetch that,
所以我可以继续，并进行预取，
even though it's not in sequential order of the other pages,
即使它不是按其他页面的顺序排列的，
and there's just another example,
这又是另一个例子，
why we want to do this on the side of the database system and not the OS.
为什么我们要在数据库系统而不是操作系统端做这个。
The next optimization we can do is called scan sharing,
我们可以做的下一个优化是扫描共享，
sometimes called synchronized scans in some of the older systems.
在一些较旧的系统中，有时称为同步扫描。
The basic idea here is a bunch of queries show up,
这里的基本思想是显示一系列查询，
they want to access to the same table,
他们想要访问同一张表，
one of them gets started and start scanning through the pages,
其中一个开始扫描页面，
and we can recognize that they need the same data,
我们可以认识到，他们需要相同的数据，
so [piggy] back off of them
所以，我们返回给它们，
and our cursor attaches their cursor
我们的游标连接到他们的游标上，
and we read the same pages at the same time,
我们同时读取相同的页面，
so we remove the redundant I/O.
所以我们去掉了多余的 I/O 。
So this is different than result caching,
所以这和结果缓存是不同的，
which we won't want to talk about the semester,
我们不想在这个学期谈论，
result caching, basically query shows up, I compute some answer,
结果缓存，是查询出现，我计算出了一些答案，
I save that result in a cache,
我将结果保存在缓存中，
query, same query shows up again,
同样的查询再次出现，
potentially slightly different, which is harder to do,
可能略有不同，这很难做到，
but say the same query shows up again,
但假设相同的查询再次出现，
I have to rerun the query,
我必须重新运行查询，
I just, I just send, send the result back.
我只是把结果发回去，
The scan sharing is really at the low physical levels of the access method,
扫描共享实际上是在访问方法的低物理级别，
how we're actually scanning the pages,
我们扫描页面的方式，
we can recognize that,
我们可以认识到，
the two queries need to read the same thing
两个查询需要读取相同的内容，
and therefore, we, we can reuse any pages as we go along and fetch them,
所以，我们可以在执行过程中重用任何页面并获取它们，
so we don't have conflicting cursors trying to read the same pages at the same time.
这样就不会有试图同时读取相同页面的冲突游标。
All right, so this is repeating what I just said,
好的，这是重复我刚才所说的，
for the DB2, SQL Server, Teradata and Postgres,
对于 DB2, SQL Server, Teradata 和 Postgres ，
they actually support the full scan sharing,
他们支持完全扫描共享，
for queries that aren't exactly the same,
对于不完全相同的查询，
but at least they're, they're reading the same tables.
但至少它们正在读取相同的表。
In Oracle, they only support cursor sharing for queries that show up that look exactly the same,
在 Oracle 中，它们只支持看起来完全相同的查询的游标共享，
I mean literally exactly the same,
我的意思是字面上完全相同，
because they're basically hashing the string, seeing whether there's a match,
因为他们是对字符串做哈希，看看是否有匹配，
like if you go look at the documentation,
如果你查看文档，
like, if you have queries like SELECT * FROM employees,
例如，如果你有 SELECT * FROM employees 这样的查询，
SELECT * FROM Employees of the capital E
SELECT * FROM Employees ，大写字母 E ，
or an extra space before the FROM clause,
或者有额外的空格在 FROM 子句前，
these won't match,
它们不会匹配，
because when you hash the strings they're not the same,
因为当你对字符串进行哈希时，它们并不相同，
so it has to literally be the exact same query, run at the exact same time
所以，它必须是完全相同的查询，在完全相同的时间运行，
and and then they can share it.
然后它们可以共享它。
So conception looks like this,
所以构思看起来是这样的，
so say I have query 1,
假设我有查询一，
let's do a summation on the val column from table A,
让我们对表 A 中的 val 列进行求和，
so attaches a cursor to the pages,
所以将游标附加到页面上，
starts reading them, fetching them into the buffer pool,
开始读取它们，并将它们提取到缓冲池中，
first thing it gets page0, that's not there,
它首先获取 page0 ，它不在那里，
so puts that in memory, goes down to page2, and so forth, right,
所以把它放在内存中，转到 page2 ，等等，
so now we get to page3,
现在我们获取 page3 ，
and we haven't talked about the eviction policy,
我们还没有讨论驱逐策略，
but page0 is the last one was used,
但 page0 是最后一个用过的，
so we go ahead and evict page0 and put in page3,
所以我们继续，把 page0 逐出，然后放入 page3 ，
but, now Q2 shows up,
但是现在， Q2 出现了，
wants to compute an average instead of summation on the same table, though,
希望在同一张表上计算平均值而不是求和，
so the naive thing to do is,
所以简单的做法是，
have it start at the beginning,
让它从开头开始，
just like the first cursor,
就像第一个光标一样，
and just scan down and read the pages at the same time,
只需同时向下扫描，并读取页面，
but obviously this is stupid,
但这显然是愚蠢的，
because in this scenario here,
因为在这种情况下，
we just, the Q2 needs to read page0,
我们只需要， Q2 需要读取 page0 ，
but Q1 just got that evicted from the buffer pool, right,
但 Q1 刚刚将其从缓冲池中逐出，
so the first thing we would do here is,
所以我们在这里要做的第一件事是，
if you want to Q2,
如果你想要 Q2 ，
we had to evict page2, to put page0 in,
我们必须逐出 page2 ，放入 page0 ，
but again, we just got rid of page0,
但是，我们刚刚逐出了 page0 ，
so the better thing to do is,
所以，更好的做法是，
you attach Q2 to Q1,
你将 Q2 附加到 Q1 上，
again at the lowest level as you scan the table,
在扫描表格时的最低级别，
and let Q2 ride along Q1,
让 Q2 随着 Q1 ，
see all the pages that it sees and processes them accordingly,
看到它看到的所有页面，并相应地处理它们，
and then Q1 goes away,
然后 Q1 消失了，
but then Q2 recognizes,
但是 Q2 意识到，
oh, there's a bunch of pages at the top of the table that I missed,
哦，在表的顶部有一堆我遗漏的页面，
let me go back and and get get all those
让我返回并获取所有这些，
and then compute my query.
然后计算我的查询。
All right,
好的，
what's the potential problem with this?
这有什么潜在的问题？
Yes.
是的。
So it's hard to implement, not that hard.
所以，它很难实现，没那么难。
Says, if the aggregate function depends on the ordering of the data,
说如果聚合函数依赖于数据的顺序，
which again, relational model, it doesn't, with no functions, yes,
再次，关系模型不依赖于，如果没有函数，是的，
you're close to it,
你接近了，
but basically say you had a LIMIT clause, right,
但是假如你有一个 LIMIT 子句，
right, I want to get the first 100 tuples
我想得到前 100 个 tuple ，
and compute the average on that,
然后计算它的平均值，
again, relational models unordered,
再次，关系型模型是无序的，
so technically, it's correct,
所以，从技术上讲，这是正确的，
if Q2 starts at page0 versus page3,
如果 Q2 从 page0 开始，而不是 page3 ，
and again it gets 100 tuples compute the average,
它获取 100 个 tuple 计算平均值，
both answers are technically correct,
这两个答案在技术上都是正确的，
from the application perspective, this looks [] up,
从应用程序的角度来看，这看起来很糟糕，
because now you got queries,
因为现在你收到查询，
the same query at two different times show up with different results.
同一查询在两个不同的时间显示不同的结果。
So I was being glib and I said,
所以我是未经思考的说，
oh yeah, it's not that hard to implement,
哦，是的，这并不是很难实现，
because you attach the cursor,
因为你附加了游标，
again, if there's no, if there's no ordering constraints, it's easy,
如果没有排序约束，这很容易，
but if you need to make sure that,
但是，如果你需要确保，
your queries produce the same results over and over again,
你的查询一遍又一遍地产生相同的结果，
then this can be a bit tricky,
那么这可能有点棘手，
this is part of the reason,
这也是部分原因，
again, I'm not trying to bash Oracle,
我不是想抨击 Oracle ，
like, the easiest thing to do is,
比如，最容易做的事情是，
if it's exact same query, I'll do cursor sharing,
如果是完全相同的查询，我会进行游标共享，
the tricky thing is to figure out,
棘手的事情是弄清楚，
to understand the semantics of what the queries actually wants to do,
理解查询实际想要做的事情的语义，
to then identify when is it safe to attach the, you know, one cursor to another
然后确定何时将一个游标连接到另一个游标是安全的，
and then how to maybe go back and and get more results as needed.
然后如何返回，并根据需要获得更多结果。
So this is a,
所以这是一个，
going sort of extreme scan sharing is this idea called continuous scan sharing,
一种极端的扫描共享是一种称为连续扫描共享的想法，
I'll say up front, too,
首先，我也要说，
that no real system does this,
没有真正的系统做这个，
but I just like it,
但我只是喜欢它，
because it's a different way to think about how to build a system.
因为这是一种思考如何构建系统的不同方式。
So again, going back to his point,
所以，回到他的观点上，
he said it would be hard to implement the scan sharing,
他说实施扫描共享是困难的，
potentially, yes, right,
潜在的，是的，
but what if you just did the dumbest thing,
但是如果你只是做最简单的事情，
just everything due scan sharing,
所有的东西都应该扫描共享，
because the cursor just running all the time,
因为游标一直在运行，
so it literally reads one page after another,
所以它会一页接一页地读取，
brings that into your buffer pool
把它放到你的缓冲池里，
and then when you're done,
然后当你完成了，
just look back around and does it all over again.
就会回来，重新来一遍。
So now when a query shows up,
所以现在当一个查询出现时，
you just kind of pop along whenever it's going
你只是在它进行的时候突然出现，
and then get what you need
然后得到你需要的东西，
and then you go away and you're done.
然后你离开，你就完成了。
Good idea or bad idea,
好主意还是坏主意，
with that heard bad, why?
听起来很糟糕，为什么。
So assuming it's [] lab,
所以，假设这是一个[]的实验，
assuming every query is doing maybe a full table scan
假设每个查询都在执行可能是全表扫描，
or almost a full table scan.
或者几乎是全表扫描。
So, would you have a table,
所以，你会有一张表，
so you, you could maybe say,
所以你可能会说，
you know, the cursor doesn't get fired,
游标不会被触发，
until the query shows that touches the table?
直到查询显示它触及了表？
That.
那个。
Yeah, but,
是的，但是，
well,
好的，
say you have to do that anyway for a full table scan,
假设你必须做全表扫描，
because the table doesn't fit in memory anyway.
因为表无论如何都无法放入内存中。
So.
所以。
Yes.
是的。
So, it's hard to skip around,
所以，它很难跳过，
well, in some ways, also, too,
好的，在一些方式中，
it makes your, your runtime kind of deterministic, right,
它让你的运行时间有点确定性，
because you know it's gonna be at least n,
因为你知道它至少是 n ，
where it ends the number pages, right,
它在页面编号结束，
that's just for scans,
那只是对于扫描，
JOINs or [], other [] we haven't talked about yet.
JOINs 或其他[]，我们还没有讨论。
If it's on [],
如果它在[]上，
you've already paid for the hardware, ignoring energy costs,
你已经支付了硬件费用，忽略能源成本，
then you know this is kind of okay,
那么这是可以接受的，
but if it's running in the Cloud,
但如果它在云上运行，
you actually paying per IOP,
你实际上是按 IOP 付费的，
then this is actually terrible, right,
那么这很糟糕，
because you end up reading more data than you potentially actually need,
因为你最终读取的数据比你实际需要的要多，
so I was saying there's only one prototype I know that did this,
我是说，我知道只有一个原型做到这个，
out of, out of ETH Zurich, called Crescando,
出自苏黎世联邦理工学院，叫做 Crescando ，
and they built it specifically for a telecom business,
他们专门为电信业务构建了它，
where they needed deterministic runtimes of queries,
在那里他们需要确定性的查询运行时，
but this was a few years ago
但这是几年前的事了，
and there was another prototype, it had the same kind of thing.
有另一个原型，它也有同样的事情。
So it's an interesting idea,
所以这是一个有趣的想法，
it's a different way to think of a system that's unorthodox,
这是一种不同的方式来思考一个非正统的系统，
like present a different way to think things,
呈现一种不同的方式来考虑事情，
I love databases,
我喜欢数据库，
there's so many different ways to solve the same problem,
有很多不同的方法可以解决同样的问题。
again, it was bad.
这是糟糕的。
So last optimization you talk about is called buffer pool bypass,
最后讨论的优化称为缓冲池旁路，
and the idea here is that,
这里的想法是，
if we have a query that's running a sequential scan,
如果我们有一个运行顺序扫描的查询，
you know, we had to bring things off a disk into memory,
我们必须把磁盘上的东西放到内存中，
but maybe we don't want to put it into our buffer pool,
但也许我们不想把它放到我们的缓冲池中，
because one need to pay for the maintenance cost of the buffer pool,
因为人们需要支付缓冲池的维护成本，
in the page, take a latch, update things and stuff and so forth, right,
在页面中，获取一个 latch ，更新东西，等等，
and then also too, if we're doing sequential scan,
而且，如果我们进行顺序扫描，
the the data we just read may not actually be useful,
我们刚刚读取的数据可能并不有用，
well, it's not gonna be useful for our query,
它对我们的查询没有用处，
because we're going sequentially scan,
因为我们将按顺序扫描，
we're only going to be the the table once usually
我们通常只会访问一次表，
and so rather than having all these different, these different, you know, workers
所以，不是拥有所有这些不同的 worker ，
running at the same time, doing sequential scans and [polluting] the page table,
在相同的时间运行，做顺序扫描和[污染]页表，
what if we just give every worker its own little piece of memory,
如果我们只给每个 worker 自己的一小部分内存，
like a working memory,
比如一个工作内存，
and then any page we read,
然后，我们读到的任何页面，
we put into that, that worker's memory,
我们都会放入那个 worker 的内存中，
yes, you could have duplicates, it only works,
是的，你可以有重复，它只工作，
if it's read only, you can't do writes,
如果它是只读的，你不能写入，
and that way it's just like a circular buffer,
这样，它就像一个循环缓冲区，
we just keep filling up and wrap around.
我们只是不断地填满，绕来绕去。
So a bunch of systems support this,
所以很多系统都支持这个，
Oracle, SQL Server, Postgres and Informix,
Oracle, SQL Server, Postgres 和 Informix ，
I think this originated Informix and they call it Light Scans,
我认为这起源于 Informix ，他们称之为轻扫描，
light meaning, because again, you don't touch that sort of heavyweight page table in the buffer pool.
轻的意思，因为，你不会触及缓冲池中的那种重量级页表。
And the idea here is that,
这里的想法是，
I can potentially not pollute my page table,
我可能不会污染我的页表，
because the data I need,
因为我需要的数据，
but the data I need is sort of local to me,
但我需要的数据是我本地的，
of course, the downside of this is that you lose the sharing capability
当然，这样做的缺点是你失去了共享的能力，
of two, two workers need the same pages at the same time,
两个 worker 同时需要相同的页面，
or one soon after another,
或者一个接一个，
then you lose that reuse possibility,
那么你就失去了重用的可能性，
but again, it's another optimization that we can do,
但是，这是我们可以进行的另一种优化，
because we control exactly what the,
因为我们准确地控制了，
you know what the queries are actually,
查询是什么，
you know what they're actually executing and touching.
它们实际执行和触及的是什么。
All right.
好的。
So we sort of dance around this idea
我们在某种程度上绕过了这个想法，
of evicting data or evicting pages from our buffer pool,
关于从我们的缓冲池中逐出数据或逐出页面，
so now we got to talk about how we're actually going to do it,
现在我们要谈谈我们到底要怎么做，
you need to know this because it's project one.
你需要知道这个，因为这是项目一。
So, when the execution says,
所以，当执行程序说，
okay, I'm bringing a page into memory,
好的，我要把一个页面放到内存中，
I'm going to put into a frame,
我要放进一个 frame ，
if there's no free frames,
如果没有空闲的 frame ，
it has to decide what to evict,
它必须决定要驱逐什么，
it's a cache, this should not be groundbreaking.
这是一个缓存，这不应该是开创性的。
So the [budget] of different metrics or objectives, we have to consider in our eviction policy,
所以，我们必须在驱逐策略中考虑的不同指标或目标的[预算]，
that's going to depend on various factors of our implementation of our database system,
将取决于我们实施数据库系统的各种因素，
obviously, we want our eviction policy to be correct, right,
显然，我们希望我们的驱逐策略是正确的，
we don't want to evict a page,
我们不想驱逐一页，
then immediately that page is the most, you know, the most used thing,
然后马上那一页是最常用的，
and therefore we keep reading and writing it from disk over and over again,
因此我们一遍又一遍地从磁盘上读写它，
could that be bad,
这会是糟糕的，
we want our eviction policy to be fast, right,
我们希望我们的驱逐策略是快速的，
we, we don't want, you know, it's a,
我们不想它是一个，
we're using an NP-complete algorithm or exponential algorithm,
我们使用的是 NP 完全算法或指数算法，
we don't want to take three seconds to decide what page to evict,
我们不想花三秒钟来决定驱逐哪一页，
because [monitor] go read it from disk,
因为[监视器]会从磁盘上读取它，
that would have a lot faster in the first place.
一开始，这会快得多。
And related to this,
与此相关的是，
we also don't want to pay a big cost
我们也不想花费很大的成本，
of maintaining the metadata, we need to keep track of how pages are being accessed,
关于维护我们需要跟踪页面是如何被访问的元数据，
so that we can make a decision what to evict.
这样我们才能决定驱逐什么。
So again, this is the oldest problem in computer science,
所以，这又是计算机科学中最古老的问题，
the other oldest problem in computer science is naming something or naming a system,
另一个计算机科学中最古老的问题是命名某个东西或命名一个系统，
we can talk about how BusTub got named,
我们可以谈谈 BusTub 是怎么命名的，
but, like everyone has a caching paper,
但是，就像每个人都有一张缓存[纸]，
I think I have two.
我想我有两张。
So the most obvious easy thing to do is do LRU, least-recently use,
所以最明显容易做的事情是 LRU ，最近最少使用，
the basic idea here is just maintain a timestamp or keep track a link, a linked list
这里的基本思想是维护一个时间戳或跟踪一个链表，
of when when pages were last touched,
关于页面最后一次是什么时候访问的，
and then when it comes time to evict a page,
然后，当需要驱逐页面时，
we just go to the tail end of the linked list
我们只需转到链表的末尾，
and pop, pop whatever is there,
然后弹出那里的任何内容，
and you know that one hasn't been accessed in a while,
那个有一段时间没人访问了，
we go ahead and evict it.
我们继续前进，把它驱逐出去。
So say here Q1 wants to touch page1,
假设 Q1 想要访问 page1 ，
page1 is already in our linked list,
page1 已经在我们的链接列表中了，
so we just move it to the front, to the head,
所以，我们只是将其移到前面，移到头部，
and then now say another query wants to touch access page5,
然后现在假设另一个查询想要访问 page5 ，
but page5 is not in memory,
但 page5 不在内存中，
so we go ahead and evict page2,
所以，我们继续，驱逐 page2 ，
because it's at the end, right,
因为它在末尾，
this should not be news to anyone.
这对任何人来说都不应该是新闻。
So another way to achieve the same thing
实现相同目的的另一种方法是，
without tracking the actual timestamps in this linked list is
在不跟踪该链表中的实际时间戳的情况下，
to use an approximation algorithm called CLOCK,
使用一种称为 CLOCK 的近似算法，
who here has heard a CLOCK before,
在座的谁以前听到过 CLOCK ，
less than five, okay,
不到五个，好的，
and so clock, a clock is using a bunch of other systems as well,
clock 也在使用一系列其他系统，
I think Linux uses this for its page cache or page table,
我认为 Linux 将其用于页面缓存或页表，
they use a multi hand clock,
他们使用多指针 clock ，
which we don't need to know about that,
我们不需要知道这个，
but the basic idea here is that,
但这里的基本思想是，
instead of keeping track of like the exact ordering of of of pages in LRU,
不是像 LRU 中那样跟踪页面的确切顺序，
instead we just give a, use a simple reference bit for every page,
相反，我们只为我们每个页面提供一个简单的引用位，
that we use to keep track of,
我们用来跟踪，
we set to 1, whenever it's accessed,
每当它被访问时，我们就设置 1 ，
whenever it's written to or read.
无论它是写入或读取。
And the idea here is that,
这里的想法是，
we'll have this clock hand sweep around and look at all our pages,
我们有这个表针扫过查看我们所有的页面，
and if the bit set to 1, set it to 0,
如果位设置为 1 ，将其设置为 0 ，
if it is set to 0, then we go ahead and evict it, right.
如果它被设置为 0 ，我们继续并驱逐它。
So say we have four pages,
假设我们有四页，
we get, reference, bit reference bit, we set the 0,
我们有引用位，我们设置为 0 ，
and then, say page1 gets accessed by a query,
然后，假设 page1 被一个查询访问，
we go ahead and set the reference bit to 1,
我们继续，并将引用位设置为 1 ，
and then now let's say,
现在让我们假设，
another query wants a page that's not in a buffer pool,
另一个查询想要一个不在缓冲池中的页面，
so we got to decide which of these four we want to evict,
所以我们必须决定这四个中的想要驱逐哪一个，
so we go ahead and the clock starts at some starting point,
所以我们继续，时钟从某个起点开始，
it looks at the reference bit,
它查看引用位，
if it's set to 1, we set it to 0
如果它设置为 1 ，我们将其设置为 0 ，
and then move on to the next one,
然后转到下一个，
in here, at page two, the reference bit is set to 0,
在这里， page2 引用位设置为 0 ，
so therefore we know the last time the clock swept it around and looked for pages to evict,
所以，我们知道时钟最后一次扫过并寻找要驱逐的页面时，
it wasn't touched,
它没有被访问，
so therefore, this is safe to evict,
所以，这是可以安全驱逐的，
we go ahead and remove it, replace it with another one,
我们继续，把它移走，用另一个取代它，
and then say the other page three and four, they both accessed,
然后比如其他 page3 和 page4 ，它们都被访问，
the clock sweeps around, sets their bit to 0,
时钟扫过，将它们的位设置为 0 ，
and then so far to come to here,
然后一直到这里，
and then now we're back to page1,
然后现在我们回到 page1 ，
it wasn't accessed as the last time you saw it,
它不像你最后一次看到它时那样被访问，
so we go ahead and pick this one.
所以我们继续，选择这个。
This is a good idea or a bad idea?
这是一个好主意，还是一个坏主意？
It seems good,
这似乎很好，
in that it allows us to have a lot less storage,
因为它允许我们拥有更少的存储空间，
since we only need one bit per,
因为我们只需要一个位，
but the downside seems like it's going to evict,
但缺点似乎是它将驱逐，
even if we don't need the room,
即使我们不需要空间，
so we might have like fewer hits.
所以我们可能会有更少的命中。
So, so he got the first part right,
所以，他的第一部分是正确的，
the first part said this is nice,
第一部分说这很好，
because the metadata overhead is low,
因为元数据的开销很低，
because it's just a bit per page,
因为它只是每页一位，
you store that as a as a contiguous big, big vector,
你可以把它存储为一个连续的大的向量，
that's easy to do,
这很容易做到，
but then the second one you said like you might evict things that you don't, shouldn't, shouldn't need evict,
但是你说的第二个你可能会驱逐你不应该驱逐的东西，
the clock only runs, like you only start the, the, the sweep,
时钟只会运行清扫，
whenever you need to evict,
在你需要驱逐的时候，
so it's not just running the background all the time,
所以，它不是一直在运行在后台，
yeah, we don't want to do that.
是的，我们不想这么做。
Yes.
是的。
Yes, so he said, and he's correct,
是的，他说的是，他说的没错，
that in case of clock and actually LRU,
在 clock 和 LRU 的情况下，
they both have this problem,
他们都有这个问题，
we're not keeping track of the frequency in which pages are accessed,
我们没有跟踪页面被访问的频率，
and so this makes them susceptible to two problems.
因此，这使得他们容易受到两个问题的影响。
So the first one is what he said down here,
第一个是他在这里说的，
like in both clock and LRU,
在 clock 和 LRU 中，
we're only tracking when they're accessed,
我们只跟踪它们被访问的时间，
not, not how often they were accessed,
而不是它们被访问的频率，
and in both cases also too,
在这两种情况下，
they're susceptible to a problem called sequential flooding,
它们也容易受到一种称为顺序洪水的问题的影响，
and this is the problem where,
这就是问题所在，
if we're running sequential scans,
如果我们在进行顺序扫描，
we gotta go fetch pages from disk put into our buffer pool,
我们必须从磁盘中获取页面，放入我们的缓冲池，
but if we're tracking the last time they were used,
但如果我们跟踪它们最后一次被使用的时间，
the the last page I just got got for my sequential scan
我刚获得的用于顺序扫描的最后一个页面，
is the most one that's recently used,
就是最近使用的那个，
but for that sequential scan, it's actually the most useful one, sorry, least useful one,
但对于顺序扫描，它实际上是最有用的，抱歉，也是最不有用的，
because it just the page that is read,
因为这是正在读取的那一页，
I'm not going to go back and read it again, right.
我不打算回去再读取一遍。
And in some cases, for lot workloads,
在某些情况下，对于许多工作负载，
it's kind of like you want the most recently used one,
这有点像最近使用的那个，
it's a gross, a gross approximation,
这是一个粗略估计，
but, another way to think about it, right.
但是另一种方式思考它的方式。
Again, so like this,
比如，就像这样，
I have a query went to a SELECT * FROM a table,
我有一个查询 SELECT * FROM 一张表，
but we're only going to get one ID or one record
但我们只获取一个 ID 或一条记录，
and say that's in page0,
比如它在 page0 ，
so we go put page0 in in our, in our buffer pool,
所以我们把 page0 放入我们的缓冲池中，
then we have our OLAP query,
然后，我们的 OLAP 查询，
that's going to scan the entire table
将扫描整个表，
and go fetch all the pages at the entire table,
并获取整个表中的所有页面，
but when it gets to page3,
但当它到了 page3 ，
we don't have any space,
我们就没有空间了，
so in, for these pages here,
所以，对于这些页面，
the least recently used page is page0,
最近最少使用的页面是 page0 ，
so I'm going to go ahead and evict that,
所以我要继续下去，把它驱逐出去，
and put in page3,
放入 page3 ，
but if another query comes along,
但如果出现另一个查询，
it does the same thing the first guy did
它会做第一个做的相同的事情，
and goes gets page1 or once once, record one in page1,
获取 page1 或 page1 中的记录一，
that's actually the page I wanted, I need,
这实际上就是我想要的页面，
but I just evicted it,
但我刚刚驱逐了它，
so this is the worst thing you could do, right.
所以这是你能做的最糟糕的事了。
And so sequential flooding is a problem,
所以，顺序洪水是一个问题，
because, again, if we do most of these point queries
因为，如果我们执行大多数这些点查询，
and then all sudden a query shows up,
然后突然出现一个查询，
it's going to blow away any useful information we've collected in our in our LRU or clock metadata.
它将摧毁我们在 LRU 或 CLOCK 元数据中收集的任何有用信息。
So the solution to this is called LRU-K,
解决这个问题的方法叫做 LRU-K ，
the idea here is,
这里的想法是，
you just keep track of the last k times a page was accessed,
你跟踪页面最近 k 次的访问次数，
and then when it comes time to decide what to evict,
然后，当决定驱逐什么时，
you compute the interval between the last time, last time or sorry the k times it was accessed,
你计算上次，抱歉， k 次访问之间的时间间隔，
and whatever one has the largest interval, meaning the time it was accessed,
任何一个有最大的间隔，也就是它被访问的时间，
k-1 or k-2 times,
k-1 或 k-2 次，
that interval is the largest,
这个间隔就是最大的，
then you know that it's likely to not be used in in the future
然后你知道它很可能在未来不会被使用，
and therefore you can, you can go ahead and remove it,
因此你可以继续并移除它，
you think regular LRU is basically LRU-K, where k equals 1, right.
你可以认为普通的 LRU 就是 LRU-K ，其中 k 等于 1 。
And with 2 or 3 or whatever,
对于 2 或 3 或其他任何东西，
most systems use 2,
大多数系统使用 2 ，
if you can use this,
如果你能用这个的话，
they just keep track of like the last two times,
它们只会记录最近两次的情况，
and I'd say what's the time between the two of those,
这两者之间的时间是多少，
and I take the one that is the largest.
我选最大的那个。
And so, of course, this is susceptible to another problem,
所以，当然，这很容易受到另一个问题的影响，
where, I I fetch a page in
我取了一个页面，
and I haven't accessed it twice yet,
但我还没有访问过它两次，
so the interval is essentially infinity,
所以间隔是无穷大，
and then it go ahead and get gets immediately evicted,
然后它继续，立即被驱逐，
but say that actually is the hot page,
但是加入这实际上是热门页面，
and I want to keep that in memory,
我想把它留在内存中，
but because I keep evicting it, I lose that,
但因为我一直在驱逐它，我失去了它，
I don't have any history of it.
我没有这方面的任何历史。
So the way to solve this is that,
所以解决这个问题的方法是，
you maintain a in memory hash table
你在内存中维护一个哈希表
that keeps track of, here's the last couple pages that I've evicted, on disk,
来跟踪，这是我驱逐的最后几个页面，在磁盘上，
and here's the here's when they were accessed, the timestamp,
这是它们被访问的时候，时间戳，
so that when I fetch a page back in after it was just removed,
所以当我取回一个页面时，它刚刚被删除，
at least now have a history for it
我现在至少有它的历史，
and not assume that it's that it's infinity.
而不是假设它是无穷大的。
And that means that over time,
这意味着随着时间的推移，
you'll be able to get information you need to compute the correct interval for pages,
你将能够获得计算页面正确间隔所需的信息，
when you know when the first time they're brought into memory,
当你知道页面第一次被放入内存的时间时，
and again, it's self correcting,
它是自我修正的，
because again, if I bring something into memory,
因为如果我把一些东西放入内存，
but then never go fetch it again,
然后再也不去取它，
it'll get removed from my ephemeral cache,
它就会从我的临时缓存中被删除，
and whenever I need it again,
每当我再次需要它的时候，
I won't have that history,
我就不会有那个历史，
and I don't know, I should evict it.
我不知道我应该驱逐它。
It's a simple solution to a simple problem,
这是一个简单问题的简单解决方案，
surprisingly, this was not invented until the 90s
令人惊讶的是，这是直到 90 年代才发明的，
and as far as I can tell,
据我所知，
only Postgres and SQL Server actually do this,
只有 Postgres 和 SQL Server 做到了这个，
and this' why I like open source things,
这就是为什么我喜欢开放源码的东西，
because there's actually the the mailing list [] post for the Postgres people in 2002,
因为在 2002 年有一篇给 Postgres 人的邮件列表记录帖子说，
saying hey, this LRU-K seems like a good idea,
嘿，这个 LRU-K 看起来是个好主意，
we should do it, right,
我们应该做它，
and they implement it.
他们就实现了它。
So MySQL doesn't do exactly LRU-K as I define,
MySQL 没有做我定义 LRU-K ，
but they use a sort of approximate one
但他们使用了一种近似的方法，
and the way they do this is that,
他们这样做的方式是，
they logically divide up the linked list for the the the LRU page page list
他们逻辑地划分 LRU 页面列表的链表，
and they have two different sections or regions,
他们有两个不同的部分或区域，
they have like the the, the, the young region, the old region,
他们有比如， young 区域， old 区域，
and for each of these two different regions,
对于这两个不同的区域，
you have a different head pointer,
你有一个不同的头指针，
where you would insert new entries.
你可以在其中插入新条目。
So let's say that I have a query,
假设我有一个问题，
I want to touch page1,
我想要访问 page1 ，
it's not in memory,
它不在内存中，
I got, So I therefore I have to put it into my buffer pool,
因此，我必须将其放入我的缓冲池中，
and when I want to add it to my linked list here,
当我想要将它添加到我的链表中时，
because page1 is not already in the linked list,
因为 page1 还不在链表中，
I'm going to add it to the old region
我会将它添加到旧区域中，
and I'll insert it where the head pointer is,
并将其插入到头指针所在的位置，
so it will evict page8 and put page1 there,
因此，它将驱逐 page8 ，并将 page1 放在那里，
now if if page1 is never accessed again,
现在，如果 page1 再也不被访问，
it'll slowly make its way to the end of the the linked list
它将缓慢地到达链表的末尾，
and then get evicted,
然后被逐出，
but if say, Q2 comes along
但如果 Q2 出现了，
and it touches page1 again,
它又一次访问了 page1 ，
we would identify that it already exists in my, my linked list
我们会发现它已经存在于我的链表中，
and it's in the old region,
并且它位于旧区域中，
so therefore I'll put it at the head of the young list, right,
因此我将把它放在新列表的头部，
and then slide everyone out.
然后滑动每个（页面）。
So again, it's approximate LRU-K,
所以，这近似于 LRU-K ，
because I'm not really keeping track of
因为我并没有真正跟踪，
like the the intervals between when when it was accessed before,
比如它被访问的时间间隔，
but just knowing that it's within this boundary of the young versus old,
但只是知道它是在新和旧之间的界限，
that I know it's like it was most likely accessed more recently,
我就知道它很可能是最近才被访问的，
whereas over here, you haven't seen it before,
而在这里，你以前从未见过它，
you haven't seen before it was added to the list.
在它被添加到列表之前，你还没有看到过。
So.
所以。
I would say also, going back to the LRU-K,
我还要说，回到 LRU-K ，
there's a bunch of other optimizations you can do,
你还可以做很多其他的优化，
that SQL Server does, but I don't think Postgres does,
SQL Server 做的，但我不认为 Postgres 做了，
where you can keep track of
你可以跟踪，
when, how, of who is accessing or referencing a page
什么时候，谁访问或引用页面，
and then that can determine whether you would,
然后可以确定你是否会，
you would say an access counts for a distinct reference
你可能会说，访问计入不同的引用，
and therefore should update the interval.
所以应该更新时间间隔。
So an example would be,
举个例子，
if I have within the same transaction,
如果我在同一个事务中，
two separate queries, access the same page,
有两个不同的查询，访问相同的页面，
well, that's in the same transaction,
这两个查询在同一个事务中，
so therefore should they be considered distinct or not,
因此它们应该被认为是不同的还是相同的，
if there's two separate transactions,
如果有两个独立的事务，
then it's very likely this page is hot,
那么这个页面很可能是热门的，
because a bunch of transactions are accessing it,
因为有一堆事务在访问它，
I think of like,
我想是，
if you log into Amazon
如果你登录 Amazon ，
and you go update, you know, your, your account information
更新你的账户信息，
and say for whatever reason that transaction updates your record twice,
不管出于什么原因，这个事务更新你的记录两次，
well, that's done in the same transaction,
这是在同一个事务中完成的，
is that consider two accesses or one,
这考虑两次访问还是一次，
and in SQL Server, they'll consider that one,
在 SQL Server 中，他们认为是一次，
I think in Postgres, they consider that two,
我认为在 Postgres 中，他们认为是两次，
all right, again, you know, a bunch of fancy things,
好的，再次，一大堆奇怪的东西，
because you know how the database system is accessing pages.
因为你知道数据库系统是如何访问页面的。
There's a bunch of policies you can do
有一堆策略你可以做，
for deciding, to relate to this like,
用来决定，关于这个，
for a given query, what page should I evict, like if,
对于给定的查询，哪个页面应该逐出，
this is related to the the, the sort of the private cache,
这与私有缓存相关，
like in, in some systems, you can say,
在一些系统中，你可以说，
all right, here's a, some subset of the pages that I [],
好的，这是我[]的页面的某个子集，
they're being backed by the buffer pool, right,
它们由缓冲池支持，
but I'm keeping track of which ones I'm accessing,
但我在追踪我访问的是哪几个，
so then I can give a hint to the buffer pool manager,
然后我可以给缓冲池管理器一个提示，
say if you don't have any more space,
如果你没有更多的空间，
here's the pages where I know I'm accessing
这是我知道我正在访问的页面，
and I don't need them again,
我不再需要它们了，
therefore, you can go ahead and evict them,
因此，你可以继续逐出他们，
now, whether or not the database system decides [] evict them or not,
现在，数据库系统决定是否逐出它们，
depends on the implementation.
取决于实现情况。
You can also maintain priority hints
你还可以维护优先级提示，
about what the type of page or you know what the object that page represents,
关于页面类型或页面代表的对象，
and then this is provided to the database system to say, you know, the buffer pool manager,
然后这个信息被提供给数据库系统缓冲池管理器，
whether something should be evicted or not.
决定是否应该逐出一些东西。
So the classic example would be,
所以经典的例子是，
if I have an index of a bunch of pages
如果我有一堆页面的索引，
and any queries that always be inserting new records,
并且任何查询总是插入新的记录，
that are just increasing the size of the, the, the data
这些记录只是增加数据的大小，
or the value that the index is based on,
或者索引所基于的值的大小，
then I know I'm gonna be always hitting the, the, the right side of the tree
那么我知道我将总是命中树的右侧，
and therefore maybe I wanna keep those pages in memory,
因此，我可能希望将这些页面保留在内存中，
and I don't care if if page2 over here gets, gets evicted,
我不关心这里的 page2 会不会被逐出，
because I'm mostly gonna be updating things on, on page6, right,
因为我主要会更新 page6 的内容，
or likewise, if I do a bunch of SELECT queries,
或者类似地，如果我执行一系列 SELECT 查询，
that I have to use the index,
必须使用索引，
well, I know the, the, the very first thing they're always going to access is the root page in the index,
我知道他们要访问的第一个东西是索引中的根页面，
so therefore that should be given higher priority than other ones,
因此，它应该得到比其他页面有更高的优先级。
now, these seem kind of like [] over like LRU-K or or other mechanisms
现在，这些看起来像是 LRU-K 或其他机制，
and they kind of are, right,
它们是一种，
and so it's like think of like as a []
所以把它想象成一个[]，
or to tell this, hey, you really probably shouldn't evict this,
或者说，嘿，你真的不应该驱逐这个，
but if you have to, yes you can,
但如果你必须这样做，是的，你可以，
but please, you know, please don't,
但是，请不要这样做，
but again, there's just additional things beyond the LRU tracking that the system is already doing.
但是，这是系统已经在做的 LRU 跟踪之外的其他事情。
The big challenge, though, when it comes to evict pages is
当涉及到逐出页面时最大的挑战是，
whether they're dirty or not.
它们是否是脏页。
So the easiest thing to do is,
所以，最简单的做法是，
if all my pages are clean,
如果我所有的页面都是干净的，
to evict them from the buffer pool is,
把它们逐出缓冲池就是，
to do nothing, you just drop the page reference in the page table,
什么都不做，只需丢弃页表中的页面引用，
you need to overwrite whatever was there before, right,
你需要覆盖以前存在的任何内容，
because you don't need to flush it back to disk,
因为你不需要将其刷新回磁盘，
if though, if all the pages are dirty
如果所有的页面都是脏的，
or the one you want evict is dirty,
或者你想要逐出的那一页是脏的，
then you got to write that to disk,
那么你必须把它写到磁盘上，
make sure it's durable and safe,
确保它是持久的和安全的，
which we cover later in the semester,
我们将在本学期晚些时候讨论，
before you can go ahead and say,
在你可以继续说（下面这些）之前，
okay, this frame is now free,
好的，这个 frame 现在是空闲的，
you can go ahead and and reuse it.
你可以继续并重新使用它。
It's actually more complicated than that,
它实际上比这复杂得多，
because you actually have to write sure the log record is flushed to disk first,
因为你必须确保日志记录首先被刷新到磁盘，
before you can flush the dirty page that the log reference talks about,
然后才能刷新日志引用所述的脏页，
we will cover that later.
我们将在稍后讨论这个。
So the reason why this is tricky to do is,
这很难做到的原因是，
because it may be the case,
因为它可能是这种情况，
given all the things we just talked about,
考虑到我们刚刚谈到的所有事情，
these priority hints, the different policies, the LRU-K stuff,
这些优先顺序的暗示，不同的政策， LRU-K 的东西，
it may be the case,
可能的情况是，
that the page you want to evict is dirty,
你想要逐出的页面是脏的，
and so that is going to require, you know, a disk flush,
所以，这将需要磁盘刷新，
but maybe the second, the second page you could evict is clean,
但可能第二个你要逐出的页面是干净的，
so should you violate the LRU-K, in that case,
那么，在这种情况下，你是否应该违反 LRU-K ，
because you're trying to get things out as fast as possible, right.
因为你试图尽快把事情[弄清楚]。
Different systems do different things,
不同的系统做不同的事情，
and this is why the enterprise systems are much better than the, than the open source systems,
这就是为什么企业系统比开源系统要好得多，
because they have all this metadata,
因为它们有所有这些元数据，
they have all these sophisticated algorithms to make these decisions,
它们有所有这些复杂的算法来做出这些决定，
because it actually depends on the speed of the hardware, right,
因为这实际上取决于硬件的速度，
if if your disk is super fast
如果你的磁盘非常快，
and yeah, I'll write it out the disk,
是的，我会把它写出到磁盘，
you know, I'll write a dirty page out right away,
我会马上写出脏页，
because that's going be fairly inexpensive operation,
因为这将是相当便宜的操作，
but if my disk is really slow
但如果我的磁盘真的很慢，
or I gotta write over the network to some slow device,
或者我必须通过网络写入某个速度较慢的设备，
then maybe I want to minimize the amount of disk writes I have to do,
那么可能我想要最大限度地减少我必须执行的磁盘写入，
when I have to evict something,
当我必须逐出一些东西，
the exact moment, I I need a, you know, I I need a space.
在我需要空间的时刻。
So there's no, there's no easy answer to this,
所以这个问题没有简单的答案，
you know, if all your pages are dirty
如果你所有的页面都是脏的，
and you need to pick one, you have to write it,
你需要挑选一个你必须写入的，
but what's one way to avoid this problem,
但是，有什么方法可以避免这个问题呢，
do not have the write [] on the critical path,
在关键路径上没有写入[]，
when you want to access a page.
当你想要访问页面时。
Background writing, right,
后台写入，对吧，
right, there's, you could have a separate thread in the background,
你可以在后台有一个单独的线程，
just walk through your page table,
只需浏览你的页表，
figure out what's dirty, make sure the log is is on disk,
找出什么是脏的，确保日志在磁盘上，
again, we'll cover that later,
再次，我们稍后会讨论这个，
but assume there's, you have to [] log first,
但是假设，你必须首先[]日志，
find pages that are dirty
找到脏的页面，
and go ahead and, and write them out,
然后继续，并将它们写出去，
and then you just flip the bit
然后你只需对位取反，
to say this page is now clean,
说这个页面现在是干净的，
so that when the eviction algorithm runs
这样当驱逐算法运行时，
and it says, okay, I have to evict something,
它说，好的，我必须逐出一些东西，
now has a bunch of options of pages that are clean, that could write out,
现在有一堆干净的页面选项，可以写出去，
or, sorry, not just drop, you know, write anything.
抱歉，不只是丢弃，可以写入任何东西。
But now there's this trade off
但是现在存在这样的权衡，
between like, should I have my system be aggressively writing out dirty pages,
比如，我的系统是否应该积极地写出脏页，
maybe interfering with queries and transactions,
可能会干扰查询和事务，
that are trying to run things [] the application,
试图运行应用程序，
or should I, you know, should I delay that,
或者我是否应该推迟一下，
but then now the problem is,
但现在的问题是，
at some point, I need to get free space
在某个时候，我需要获得空闲空间，
and all my pages are dirty,
而我所有的页面都是脏的，
it's a super hard problem
这是一个很难的问题，
and there's no easy answer.
没有简单的答案。
But all the systems are going to have some mechanism to do this kind of background writing.
但所有的系统都会有某种机制来进行这种后台写入。
Then we haven't, checkpoints are a whole other [],
我们没有，检查点是一个完全不同的[]，
checkpoints, you flush everything out,
检查点，你把所有东西都刷新出去，
but that happens every, every minutes,
但这是发生在每分钟，
not every second.
不是每秒钟。
Okay?
好的？
All right, so,
好的，所以，
now we start talking a little bit about,
现在，我们开始讨论一下，
when we do these disk writes and disk reads,
何时进行这些磁盘写入和读取，
we got to talk about,
我们得讨论一下，
how are we actually going to do that.
我们到底要怎么做。
And for this one,
对于这个，
when we, you know, when we make read and write calls to the file system,
当我们对文件系统进行读写调用时，
assuming we're running on the file system, not, not raw partitions,
假设我们在文件系统上运行，而不是在原始分区，
there's a bunch of layers below us, in our database system,
在我们的数据库系统下面有很多层，
like the OS and the file system and the hardware,
比如操作系统、文件系统和硬件，
that's gonna be clever
这将是聪明的，
and try to maximize the amount of bandwidth we that that can achieve
并试图最大化我们可以实现的带宽量，
by reordering and batching our I/O requests,
通过重新排序和批处理 I/O 请求，
part of the reason why these, the modern disk drives or SSDs or NVMe drives are so fast,
现代磁盘驱动器或 SSD 或 NVMe 驱动器速度如此之快的部分原因是，
because they have these long queues,
因为它们有很长的队列，
they can do parallel requests,
它们可以进行并行请求，
so if you just do one read at a time,
所以，如果你一次只读一次，
that's going to be super slow,
那会非常慢，
but you can batch things up
但你可以把事情分批处理，
and make sure that you're reading a bunch of contiguous data,
并确保你读取一堆连续的数据，
things will be really fast.
事情会变得很快。
But the challenge is, though,
但挑战是，
these different layers of the system below the database system,
数据库系统下面的这些不同的系统层，
don't know what the requests actually correspond to,
不知道这些请求对应于什么，
they just see reads and writes pages at some location or some address,
它们只看到读写某个位置或某个地址的页面，
they don't know,
他们不知道，
oh, this is from the background writer
哦，这是来自后台写入的，
or this is for an index
或者这是索引的，
or this is for the query, that I need to run right now.
或者这是我现在需要运行的查询的。
So you can play some games with,
所以，你可以玩一些游戏，
in, in Linux, setting the I/O priority,
在 Linux 中，设置 I/O 优先级，
but that's basically a sledgehammer,
但这是一把[大锤]，
the only thing you can really do is,
你唯一能做的是，
change the I/O priority on a per, per process level,
更改每个进程级别上的 I/O 优先级，
you can't do it on a per single request,
你不能对每个请求执行此操作，
which is what we really want.
这才是我们真正想要的。
So if you read the documentation bunch of different database systems,
如果你阅读了大量不同的数据库系统的文档，
they tell you to all get off the default Linux scheduler,
他们会告诉你，所有人都放弃默认的 Linux 调度程序，
which is the Fair scheduler,
也就是 Fair 调度程序，
and either use deadline
要么使用 deadline ，
or the simple FIFO queue noop,
要么使用简单的 FIFO 队列 noop ，
because they don't want the the database system,
因为他们不想要数据库系统，
they don't want the operating system to do a bunch of stuff,
他们不想让操作系统做一堆数据，
that that, that the database system can't control.
数据库系统无法控制的事情。
So this is why,
这就是为什么，
in most database systems,
在大多数据库系统中，
they're going to have their own little shim layer, right above the, the OS,
他们将在操作系统上方拥有自己的小[填充]层，
that's going to be responsible for keeping track of
这将负责跟踪，
what requests are outstanding for reads and writes from the buffer pool manager
缓冲池管理器中哪些未完成的读写请求，
and decide how to put things together to optimize performance,
并决定如何将它们组合在一起以优化性能，
and basically you think of determining the priorities for these different I/O requests,
基本上，你考虑确定这些不同 I/O 请求的优先级，
based on a multitude of different factors,
基于多种不同的因素，
because again, we know what the queries are trying to do,
因为，我们知道查询试图做什么，
we know what pages are in a buffer pool,
我们知道缓冲池中有哪些页面，
we know what's dirty and not dirty,
我们知道什么是脏的，什么不是脏的，
we know what are the outstanding requests.
我们知道什么是未解决的请求。
And so to try to keep track of things
所以，为了跟踪，
like what's sequential I/O versus random I/O
顺序 I/O 和随机 I/O 之类的东西，
is the request based on the critical path,
请求是基于关键路径的，
like a query needs this right now
比如查询现在就需要这个，
or is this like a background job, background, the, the background writer
或者这是后台工作，后台写入，
and therefore, you know, could have a lower priority,
所以，可能会有较低的优先级，
the data we're accessing for a table, an index, log records,
我们正在访问的表、索引、日志记录的数据，
again, the logs we want to flush as fast as possible,
我们希望尽可能快地刷新日志，
is it for ephemeral data,
它是否针对临时数据的，
like if if it's a sequencential scan for a table,
如果是对表的顺序扫描，
that's gonna have a lower priority,
它将有较低的优先级，
then maybe random access for index,
可能会随机访问索引，
because as you traverse your B+ tree,
因为当你遍历 B+ 树时，
you're holding latches as you go down
你会在向下移动时持有 latch ，
and therefore that's going prevent other threads from running the same time,
因此这将阻止其他线程同时运行，
but if you query, your scan query is a little bit slower,
但是，如果你的扫描队列查询速度稍慢一些，
you're technically potentially not interfering with other queries running at the same time,
从技术上讲，你可能不会干扰同时运行的其他查询，
well, that's not true,
这不是真的，
because you take, you take locks when you run queries and transactions,
因为当你运行查询和事务时，你会拿到锁，
so there's no, you know, there's no easy answer for,
所以没有简单的答案，
when one be faster than another,
当一个比另一个更快时，
you can't just,
你不能仅仅，
because it's an index, because it's a table,
因为它是一个索引，因为它是一个表，
again, the OS doesn't know that it's an index page versus a table page.
再次，操作系统不知道它是一个索引页还是一个表页。
There's also sometimes in some systems,
有时，在一些系统中，
you can have SLA service level agreements or service level objectives,
你可以有 SLA 服务级别协议或服务级别目标，
like my queries have to run within a certain deadline at a certain latency,
比如，我的查询必须在特定的最后期限内以特定的延迟运行，
and the typical way you do this is,
这样做的典型方式是，
you have different user account
你有不同的用户帐户，
and give one user account higher priority than another user account,
并为一个用户帐户赋予比另一个用户帐户更高的优先级，
like the, the frontend application has a higher priority than like, you know, nightly reporting jobs,
比如，前端应用程序具有比夜间报告作业更高的优先级，
and you do that based on user roles.
你可以根据用户角色来执行。
So the way we can get better performance
所以，我们可以获得更好的性能，
and try to avoid some of this interference from the OS is
并试图避免操作系统的某些干扰的方法是，
to use what's called direct I/O.
使用所谓的直接 I/O ，
So, all your disk operations for the most part,
所以，在很大程度上，你的所有磁盘操作，
are going to have to go through the OS API,
都必须通过 OS API ，
unless you're doing like, you know, direct kernel bypass to the hardware device,
除非你执行类似于直接，绕过内核到硬件设备的操作，
but most systems don't do that.
但大多数系统不会这样做。
And the idea here is that,
这里的想法是，
we don't want the OS to maintain its own cache, called the page cache,
我们不希望操作系统维护自己的缓存，称为页面缓存，
because we don't want the OS to buffer our reads and writes,
因为我们不希望操作系统缓冲我们的读取和写入，
we want to do that all entirely ourselves,
我们希望完全靠我们自己做这个，
because again, we want to have full control of the hardware.
因为，我们希望完全控制硬件。
So the idea is like this,
所以这个想法是这样的，
if I do a read against the file system,
如果我对文件系统执行读取，
well, the OS is gonna say,
那么操作系统会说，
oh, let me go maintain my own little buffer pool in, in the OS
哦，让我在操作系统中维护我自己的小缓冲池，
across all all the processes running global for the OS,
跨操作系统全局运行的所有进程，
and then I will store the data I need you're asking for in my page cache
然后我会将我需要的数据存储在我的页面缓存中，
and then the next time I do a read,
然后下一次我进行读取时，
I'll get it for my, for my page cache.
我会为我的页面缓存获取这些数据。
So instead we want to bypass this and go around it
所以，我们想要绕过这个，绕过它，
and go directly to the hardware
直接进入硬件，
and not have the OS buffer anything.
而不是让操作系统缓冲任何东西。
So most systems use direct I/O,
所以大多数系统使用直接 I/O ，
most systems use direct I/O by default,
大多数系统默认使用直接 I/O ，
there is only one system that does not,
只有一个系统不是这样的，
anyone to guess what it is.
有人猜猜是什么。
Say SingleStore, no.
SingleStore ，不是。
MySQL, no.
MySQL ，不是。
It's Postgres, right,
它是 Postgres ，
Postgres, because it's a relic from the 80s,
Postgres ，因为它是八十年代的遗物，
they rely heavily on the OS page cache,
他们严重依赖操作系统页面缓存，
it calls,
它调用，
and so when you allocate a buffer pool in Postgres,
当你在 Postgres 中分配缓冲池时，
you set, it's like 30 40 percent of the amount of memory that's on the box,
你设置，它大约是机器上内存量的 30-40% ，
MySQL and every other database system tells you use 80% of the memory, that's available in the box,
MySQL 和所有其他数据库系统都会告诉你使用机箱中可用内存的 80% ，
because in Postgres,
因为在 Postgres 中，
they want some of the memory to be for the the page cache and the OS,
他们想要一些内存用于页面缓存和操作系统，
some of the memory for the database system.
一些内存用于数据库系统。
So what's the problem with this,
那么，这有什么问题，
well, now I got redundant copies of my pages,
现在我得到了我的页面的多余副本，
the OS is going to have a copy of my page,
操作系统将拥有我的页面的副本，
and my database system is going to have a copy of my page,
我的数据库系统将拥有我的页面的副本，
same thing for both reads and writes,
读和写都是一样的，
and then the, the, the, the database system is going to have its own policy
然后，数据库系统将有自己的策略，
of how to decide what pages to evict,
来决定如何逐出哪些页面，
but then, just because I evict it from my buffer pool in my, in my database system,
但是，因为我在我的数据库系统中从我的缓冲池中逐出它，
the OS can decide evict anyway it wants to,
操作系统就可以随心所欲地决定逐出它，
and again, it doesn't know what the pages actually represent,
再说一次，它不知道页面实际上代表了什么，
and then you also lose control, when things actually get flushed out the disk,
然后，你也会失去控制，当东西刷新到磁盘时，
unless you're careful.
除非你很小心，
So, let's see how far you guys can get these answers here,
所以，让我们看看你们能在这里得到这些答案，
even if you haven't taken the OS class.
即使你没有上过操作系统课程。
So if you call fwrite, what happens?
所以，如果你调用 fwrite ，会发生什么？
I open a file, right,
我打开一个文件，
say my database file,
比如我的数据库文件，
I have my buffer pool manager bring a page
我让我的缓冲池管理器带来一个页面，
in another query updates it,
在其他查询中更新它，
the page is dirty,
页面脏了，
I call fwrite to write that page out the disk,
我调用 fwrite 将那一页写出磁盘，
What happens?
会发生什么事？
Assuming we were not using direct I/O,
假设我们没有使用直接 I/O ，
the page lands in the OS page cache,
页面位于操作系统页面缓存中，
because the operating system is trying to be clever
因为操作系统试图变得更聪明，
and trying to make things fast for you, right,
并试图让事情变得更快，
so is it on disk yet,
那么它已经存储在磁盘上了吗，
when I get, when I get, when fwrite returns,
当我得到，当 fwrite 返回时，
is is my, is my data save,
我的数据保存了吗，
no, because it's in the OS page cache,
不，因为它在操作系统页面缓存中，
when is it going to be flush out the disk,
它在什么时候刷新到磁盘，
when the OS decides to do it, right,
当操作系统决定做它的时候，
but that we want to make sure our thing on disk,
但我们想要确保我们的东西在磁盘上，
so what do we call fsync,
所以我们调用 fsync ，
what does fsync do?
fsync 是做什么的？
Flush.
刷新。
Flush what?
刷新什么？
Dirty pages out the disk
磁盘上的脏页面，
and you can be clever, you kind kind of do [ranges], right,
你可以聪明，你会做[范围]，
doesn't always work
并不总是起作用，
and then the call to fsync will block,
然后调用 fsync 将被阻塞，
until the hardware comes back, says your data is persistent.
直到硬件返回，说你的数据是持久的。
The hardware can play games too,
硬件也可以玩这个游戏，
because sometimes the hardware has a little battery down there,
因为有时硬件下面有一个小电池，
so you'll get your writes,
所以你会得到你的写入，
that's still sitting, volatile memory,
那仍然在易失性内存上，
but if there's a power and you, you can, you can send in response to,
但如果有电力，你可以发送回复，
I got, I got your write,
我得到了你的写入，
but then there's a power loss,
但随后就会出现断电，
there's just enough battery juice
有足够的电池电量，
to then make sure it gets gets written to disk, right,
然后确保它被写入磁盘，
so it's not, not,
所以它不是，
always me on the NAND flash at that point,
在那个时刻，我总是在 NAND 闪存上，
but, typically, that's good enough.
但是，通常，这已经足够好了。
But what happens if fsync calls failure,
但是，如果 fsync 调用失败会发生什么，
what fsync says I can't do it for you,
如果 fync 说我不能为你做这个，
what does that mean?
那是什么意思？
Say the OS doesn't crash,
假设操作系统没有崩溃，
fsync just returns an error,
fsync 只是返回一个错误，
in Linux, it's going to mark the dirty pages are clean,
在 Linux 上，它会标记脏页是干净的，
it's not a kernel panic,
这不是内核 panic ，
it says these pages are clean,
它说这些页面是干净的，
even though fsync failed,
即使 fsync 失败了，
and then you call fsync again, it's going to,
然后再次调用 fsync ，它将会，
on those pages that you want to write the disk through your fwrite,
在你想要通过 fwrite 写入磁盘的那些页面，
it's going to come back and say, yep, I got them,
它会回来说，是的，我拿到了，
they're clean, it's on disk,
它们是干净的，在磁盘上，
but it's lying to you, right,
但它对你撒谎了，
why is it lying to you,
它为什么要对你撒谎，
because the kernel developers are worried about someone pulling out a USB stick, right,
因为内核开发人员担心有人拔出 U盘，
and then the fsync failing
然后 fsync 失败，
and having a bunch of dirt pages marked dirty in its, in its page table,
在它的页表中有一堆脏页面被标记为脏的，
that are never gonna get come back again,
这些页面再也不会回来了，
because you're never gonna put the USB stick back in again, right,
因为你再也不会把 U盘 放回去了，
is that the right thing for databases,
这对数据库来说是正确的吗，
no, right, we're not running off a usb stick.
不，是吧，我们不运行在 U盘上。
So again, we need full control of everything
所以，我们需要完全控制一切，
to make sure we're doing things right,
以确保我们做的事情是正确的，
well, it turns out that,
好的，事实证明，
people didn't know that that fsync was broken in this way for 20 years,
二十年来，人们不知道 fsync 在这种情况下是坏掉的，
so in 2018, there was a scandal called fsyncgate,
所以在 2018 年，有一起名为 fsyncgate 的丑闻，
where someone on the Postgres mailing list reported,
在 Postgres 邮件列表上有人报告说，
hey, Postgres lost some of my data,
嘿， Postgres 丢失了我的一些数据，
but I, you know, I never got a kernel panic, I never had a failure,
但是，我从来没有遇到过内核 panic ，我从来没有失败过，
and it turns out, because fsync,
事实证明，因为 fsync ，
on all these database systems,
在所有这些数据库系统上，
they would call fsync,
他们会调用 fsync ，
fsync would return to error
fsync 会返回错误，
and they just put it in a while loop and call it again,
他们只是将其放入 while 循环中，并再次调用它，
and then fsync came back and said,
然后 fsync 回来说，
yep, I got it,
是的，我得到了它，
because they marked out your pages that were dirty to clean,
因为他们标记了你的页面从脏的到干净的，
even though they were never written.
尽管它们从来没有写入。
It's not just Postgres had this problem,
不仅是 Postgres 有这个问题，
MySQL had this problem,
MySQL 有这个问题，
MongoDB had this problem
MongoDB 有这个问题，
and WiredTiger a bunch of other systems.
以及 WiredTiger ，很多其他系统。
So now what do they do,
那么现在他们怎么做，
well, if fsync fails, then then the system crashes,
如果 fsync 失败，那么系统就会崩溃，
and then you got to go figure out what's going on,
然后你就得弄清楚到底是怎么回事，
but for twenty years, people didn't know this was an issue, right.
但二十年来，人们并不知道这是一个问题。
And so this is not an issue of the page cache,
所以这不是页面缓存的问题，
but this is an example where we need to make sure we have full control
但是这是我们需要确保完全控制的例子，
of what is getting read and written from disk into memory,
从磁盘读取和写入内存，
and that when we write things out the disk,
当我们将内容写出磁盘时，
we want to make sure that it's actually save and correct,
我们希望确保它是保存和正确的，
and that the OS can lie to us,
操作系统可能会对我们撒谎，
because the OS doesn't care about databases,
因为操作系统不关心数据库，
because the OS is worried about,
因为操作系统担心f
you know, somebody with a USB stick or whatever,
有人带着 U盘或其他什么东西，
because it's trying to be a general purpose system,
因为它试图成为一个通用系统，
and so we need to make sure that,
所以，我们需要确保，
we, as a database system developers,
我们作为操作库系统开发人员，
put the mechanisms in place
将机制放在适当的位置，
to make sure that we don't, we don't get screwed.
以确保我们不会被搞砸。
Okay?
好的？
All right, so there's multiple pools other than, than what we've talked about,
好的，所以还有其他的多种池，除了我们所说的以外，
just think ephemeral caches for JOINs and things like that,
想想 JOIN 用的临时缓存和之类的东西，
we'll see that later.
我们稍后会看到这个。
Okay.
好的。
So we always be better than the operating system,
所以我们总是比操作系统更好，
despite what the Linux people say, the OS people say,
不管 Linux 的人说什么，操作系统的人说什么，
and it's because we know what the query plans are want to do,
因为我们知道查询计划要做什么，
we know how queries want to access data
我们知道查询如何访问数据，
and we can always do better things.
我们总是可以做更好的事情。
Hash tables next class,
下一节课是哈希表，
but let me talk about project #1 very, very quickly,
但让我非常快地谈谈项目一，
so you'll be implementing this in BusTub obviously,
很明显，你将在 BusTub 中实现这个，
and so you have three parts,
所以你有三个部分，
LRU-K replacement policy,
LRU-K 替换策略，
a disk scheduler, a very primitive one,
一个磁盘调度器，一个非常原始的，
and then the actual buffer pool manager instance itself.
然后是实际的缓冲池管理器实例本身。
So for the first one,
对于第一个，
there'll be a separate class that you need to implement that,
你需要一个单独的类来实现它，
basically keep track of all the pages
基本上跟踪所有页面，
and then there'll be an API to implement,
然后有要实现的 API ，
it says I need, give me, give me a page to evict,
它说我需要，给我一个要逐出的页面，
so you sort of implement that first
所以，你可以先实现它，
and then there's there's there's, you know, there's test to make sure this is actually working correctly,
然后有测试确保这个正确的工作，
if none of the pages have been touched that time you check,
如果在你检查时没有任何页面被访问，
then always return the lowest page ID,
则始终返回最低的页面 ID ，
because again, you got to fix something,
同样，你必须修复一些东西，
and so you decide what to evict based on that.
所以，你可以根据这个来逐出什么。
Next, implement is a disk scheduler,
接下来，实现一个磁盘调度器，
basically you going take a bunch of requests or different threads at the same time
基本上，你将同时处理一组请求或不同的线程，
and then have a single queue decide in which order you should apply the read and writes,
然后让单个队列决定读取和写入的顺序，
and the way you implement this, the API,
你实现这个 API 的方法，
there will be a callback mechanism
这里有一个回调机制，
through the C++ promise API, promise constructs,
通过 C++ 的 promise API, promise 构造，
and this is a function you invoke
这是一个函数，你需要调用，
once the the page, the data that the requester is waiting for is available
一旦请求者等待的页面、数据可用，
and you call that back,
你就可以回调，
it's not going to be true asynchronous I/O,
它不会是真正的异步 I/O ，
but it the, because basically the thread that makes the request will block on this call back,
但是，因为发出请求的线程将在此回调上阻塞，
But this would be the building block to do more sophisticated things,
但这将是做更复杂事情的基石，
so make sure that what you build here is thread safe.
所以，请确保你在这里构建的代码是线程安全的。
Last thing is the buffer pool manager itself
最后一件事是缓冲池管理器本身，
and this will be built on top of the LRU-K implementation and your disk scheduler,
这将建立在 LRU-K 实现和你的磁盘调度器的基础上，
and you maintain the internal data structure to read and write data using the disk scheduler
你可以使用磁盘调度器维护内部数据结构，
and keep track of what pages are free and when they're accessed,
并跟踪哪些页面是空闲的，以及何时访问这些页面，
and the thing that always trips up people every year is
而每年总是让人犯错的一件事是，
make sure you get the ordering correctly,
确保你得到了正确的顺序，
when you're pinning and unpinning.
在你 pinning 和 unpinning 的时候。
So, six might not be the right number, but don't change any other file,
所以，六可能不是正确的数字，但不要更改任何其他文件，
because everything will get over overwritten, when you load it up into GradeScope,
因为所有内容都会被覆盖，当你把它装入 GradeScope 时，
the projects are cumulative,
这些项目是累积性的，
we won't be writing solutions and then post everything on on piazza as you go along,
我们不会编写解决方案，然后将所有内容发布到 Piazza 上，
like in project #0, you have to make sure you have good code quality,
就像在项目零中，你必须确保你有良好的代码质量，
so make sure you run, make format and then check-clang-tidy,
所以，请确保你运行 make format ，然后 check-clang-tidy ，
because if you don't do this and you upload the GradeScope, you'll get a zero,
因为如果你不这样做，你上传到 GradeScope ，你会得到零，
we are having,
我们有，
for this project and all the other projects, there'll be extra credit,
这个项目和所有其他项目，将有额外的学分，
there's a leader board,
有一个排行榜，
with the additional tasks that go beyond the core requirements
有超出核心要求的额外任务，
and then you'll get ranked when you submit thing on GradeScope
当你的东西提交到 GradeScope 时，你会得到排名，
and then the the top twenty students will get will get bonus points for this project,
然后排名前 20 的学生将获得这个项目的加分，
and this will be available for all four projects
这将适用于所有四个项目，
and then the student at the end of the semester has the has the highest score of bonus points
然后在学期末的学生有最高的奖励分数，
and all the students will get a limited edition BusTub hoodie,
所有的学生都将获得一件限量版 BusTub 连帽衫，
You have to fill out a tax form, because they're limited edition,
所以你得填一张税单，因为是限量版，
they cost 5000 dollars
他们花了 5000 美元，
and again CMU will handle that the paperwork for that,
CMU 将处理这方面的文书工作，
but it's highly desirable.
但这是非常值得的。
Don't around, don't plagiarize,
不要抄袭，
because again the GradeScope has the automatic plagiarism checker
因为 GradeScope 有自动抄袭检查器，
and we go find the [] Github,
我们去找 [] 在 GitHub 上，
we put them as fake students
我们把他们当作假学生，
and if you copy them
如果你抄袭他们，
you'll get flagged.
你会被标记。